<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A plaine path to perfect vertue: deuised and found out by Mancinus a Latine poet, and translated into English by G. Turberuile gentleman</title>
            <title>De quatuor virtutibus. English</title>
            <author>Mancinus, Dominicus, fl. 1478-1491.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1568</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 135 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06809</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17244</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120309</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855508</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855508</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21003</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06809)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21003)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 573:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A plaine path to perfect vertue: deuised and found out by Mancinus a Latine poet, and translated into English by G. Turberuile gentleman</title>
                  <title>De quatuor virtutibus. English</title>
                  <author>Mancinus, Dominicus, fl. 1478-1491.</author>
                  <author>Turberville, George, 1540?-1610?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[144] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Knightrider strete, by Henry Bynneman, for Leonard Maylard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno 1568.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>A translation of: Mancinus, Dominicus.  "Mancinus de quatuor virtutibus", first published in 1584 (STC 17239.3).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: * A-H.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cardinal virtues --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Latin poetry --  Translations into English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21003:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21003:1"/>
            <p>¶ A plaine Path to perfect Vertue: <hi>Deuiſed and found out by Mancinus a Latine Poet,</hi> and tranſlated into En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh by G. Turberuile Gentleman.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ardua ad Virtutem via.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprinted at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don in Knightrider ſtrete, by Henry Bynneman,</hi> for Leonard Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lard.</p>
            <p>ANNO 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21003:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21003:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable and hys ſingular good Lady, Lady Anne, Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teſſe Warvvicke, George Turberuyle wyſheth Neſtors yeares,</hi> with all good fortune.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ithens GOD (madame) hath made Man of ſo diuine and heauenly Nature, aſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnyng hym the heade and Soueraigne of all other earthly things: pitie were it, yea ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhame, for him to debaſe his kinde, or taint himſelfe with any thing vnworthie ſo noble a Creature. Yet ſo many are the cuils and miſchiefes in this life, aſsaultyag the minde and better part of man, making him franke offer of ſuche painted pleaſures and counterfaite Fel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ie, as without great hede and prouident care, vnpoſsible is it for him to ſcape the deceitfull ſnares of alluring Vice whoſe ioy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſtet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>ſion and ful.
<pb facs="tcp:21003:3"/> So diuers are the hookes that Sinne layeth to take the Soule withall: as few of many can ſwim through the rockie Sea of this perilous life without tasting that pleaſaunt hurtefull bayte. Whiche if they once feede on, taking therin delight and pleaſure, vnawares they deuoure and ſwallow downe the hooke that brings them ſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>die and vnauoided death. Wherfore waying the danger hereof, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the great ſtore of vices, behouefull is it for vs to deuiſe ſome one remedie or other againſt this miſchief. And ſithens nothing can better haue redreſse than by his contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie (as all diſeaſes by contraries are to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured) there can not (I thinke) bee a more ſpedie or abſolute meane to auoid this mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ice, delighting in Mans decaye, than to skirmiſhe vnder the banner of Vertue, alwayes awaiting on hir, neuer doing ought contrary to hir lawes and ordinaunces. For Vertue is it that hateth <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ice, ſeeking the best it may to ſuppreſse that cankred nature of his, and withſtand his malicious attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. But ſo narow and ſtraight is the paſsage to Vertue, ſo ſundry are the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ices eke lying in awaite and ambuſhe to intercept vs, as it
<pb facs="tcp:21003:3"/> is a labour of no ſlender toile to attaine the ſame. Here might I for witneſse appeale <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotle</hi> that noble <hi>Greke</hi> and learned Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher, ſaue that the Experience it ſelfe ſufficiently maketh ſhewe therof. Yet it ſhall not be from the purpoſe to recite his opinion. He in his boke of Morall Vertues hath this Sentence: <hi>Quia Virtus medium ſibi qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi ſignum proponit, difficile eſt virtute eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe praeditum,</hi> Whiche I thus engliſhe: For that Vertue ſetts before it the Meane, as a marke and ſcope, a harde matter is it to bee Vertuous. See here (Madame) both the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the lerned Philoſopher, and his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon withall. For not alone hathe he in theſe fewe wordes affirmd it hard to attain Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, but giueth alſo a cauſe of the difficultie therin. Bicauſe (ſayth he) it conſistes vpon the meane. And in dede ſo doth it. Extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are the mortal enimies of Vertue. Vertue delighteth euer to obſerue the Meane, and flee exceſse in al things. Whatſoeuer it is that partakes with Extremes, and ſhoonnes the golden Meane, can not ſmatch of Vertue at all. Wherfore waying the difficultie of this matter, As better hap can not befall a wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring
<pb facs="tcp:21003:4"/> Pilgrim doubtfull and altogether vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine of his voyage (hauing many ways at his foote to pace in) than to chaunce vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the right Pathe to his long deſired lodge and harbor: So greater co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort can not come to a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iorneying in the vncertain progreſse of this pilgrimage of life, where Vice offers him ſundry wayes and bypathes to wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, than to finde a ready and beaten path to Vertue, there to rest and ſtay his running and vnstayd foote. Whiche ſithens it is ſo harde a matter to find out without a guide, I (madame) haue here offred my paines, as your Ladyſhip may ſe, in this litle Boke, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on great deſire to diſcouer a plaine Path to perfect Vertue, that all men might diſcerne the hie way that leades to happy life. For aſſuredly our nature of it ſelfe is chiefly bent and inclined to the yll and wicked trade. And albeit (Madame) your Ladyſhip for your owne parte are in euery poynt ſo furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with Vertue, as ſmall is youre neede of any instructour therein, beeing very well able to aduiſe your ſelfe in liuing well: yet for that the place of honoure wherein you ſitte, and your Noble State, is a Spectacle
<pb facs="tcp:21003:4"/> and Myrrour to inferiour perſons, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to frame their corrupted liues: thought it not amiſse to dedicate you this ſlender trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of mine. Hauyng deſire to publiſhe it vnder the protection of your name, for that I hope there will the moe peruſe the Booke: and in peruſing (I trust) ſhall light vpon ſome one Wholeſome leſson or other, preuai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to the increſe of Vertue and honeſt life. Whiche if doe happen, then ſhall I reioyce that it was my happe trauailyng in ſo litle a Booke to doe the Reader ſo greate a bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite, and youre Ladyſhippe haue the leſse cauſe to accuſe my bolde attempte in dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating you the ſame. Neither yet doe I cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge vnto mee the first inuention thereof, for then wrong ſhoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I doe to <hi>Mancinus,</hi> myne Authour: but for Vertues ſake was deſirous to write of Vertue, though follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing the foote and ſteppes (as it were) of an other man. If my Author be in his lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage to be liked for his deuiſe in pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning the Treatiſe, then ſhall I not (I trust) deſerue miſliking for tranſlating the ſame. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore preſumyng vpon the good acceptaunc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of this my Boke at youre Ladyſhips hande
<pb facs="tcp:21003:5"/> whome I boldely craue as Buckeler to my weake and vnarmed Muſe, and affying well in the Readers curteſie, I ende this tedious Epistle: Crauyng your long continuance of preſent ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, with good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſse in all your Life.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>To whom I rest a dayly Orator <hi>George Turberuyle.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Virtutis comes inuidia, Sed ex virtute gloria.</q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:21003:5"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <l>I Neither vvrite the nevves of Poules of late ſet out to ſale,</l>
            <l>Nor Meting of the London Maides: for novv that Fish is ſtale.</l>
            <l>The date therof is fully out, no vvonder laſteth long.</l>
            <l>I ſpeake not this vpon deſire to doe that vvriter vvrong,</l>
            <l>But for bicauſe not long ago vvithin this Citie Syn</l>
            <l>Had done a ſpoyle (as one did vvrite) and Conquerour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d byn,</l>
            <l>Diſplaying banners <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> about in proofe of Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ueſt vvoon,</l>
            <l>And ſounding Trun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as though he had the Citie ouerroon:</l>
            <l>Bicauſe (I ſay) vve mig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> renevve the battaile once againe,</l>
            <l>And reencounter Sinne afresh that ſpites at Vertues traine:</l>
            <l>To fine vve might that filthy Fiende and hideous <hi>Hydra</hi> ſlay,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Mancinus</hi> firſt, and I by him to Vertue shevv the vvay.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:21003:6"/>
            <l> For Vertue is the foe in deede vvhom Vice doth deadly hate:</l>
            <l>And euer yet betvvixt them hath there ben a foule debate.</l>
            <l>And though that Syn hath greater gard and ſouldiers moe in fielde</l>
            <l>Than Vertue hath, yet Vertue ſhall enforce the beaſt to yelde.</l>
            <l>Off shal his head from shoulders go,</l>
            <l>Synne shall be ſinne no more,</l>
            <l>The monſter Vice shall ſure decay that long the ſvvay hath bore,</l>
            <l>If you <hi>Mancinus</hi> Path enſue and follovv on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e vvay</l>
            <l>VVhich he to Lady <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ertues</hi> lodge and Palace d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> diſplay.</l>
            <l>VVhiche though perhaps vvere harde to finde or eare he vv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t about</l>
            <l>By curious ſearch and tedious toyle to shevv to ſet it out:</l>
            <l>Yet now it is ſo eaſie vvoxe by meane of his deuiſe,</l>
            <l>As vvho ſo follovves hym shal come to Vertue vvith a trice.</l>
            <l>As <hi>Ariadnas</hi> friendly tvviſt and ſlender tvvine did shovv.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:21003:6"/>
            <l> Duke <hi>Theſeus</hi> in the doubtfull den vvhich vvay vvas beſt to go</l>
            <l>From <hi>Minotaure</hi> miſshapen beaſt, halfe man and halfe a Bull,</l>
            <l>VVith gorie guts of murthred men that had his belly full:</l>
            <l>Euen ſo <hi>Mancinus</hi> by this path vvill teache thee how to ſlie</l>
            <l>The <hi>Labyrinth</hi> of lothſome ſinne vvhere Vice and he do lie,</l>
            <l>Delighting in the fall of man and feeding on his ſoule</l>
            <l>As did that Fiende vpon the men of <hi>Athens</hi> in the hole.</l>
            <l>And loke hovv much the ſoule excedes this earthly bodies maſſe,</l>
            <l>So much the monſter Synne the beaſt of <hi>Creta</hi> doth ſurpaſſe.</l>
            <l>VVherfore let be our earneſt care vvith ioyned hartes and hande</l>
            <l>Againſt this Sinne on Vertues ſide vvith ſworde and ſhielde to ſtande.</l>
            <l>March on your vvay by <hi>Prudence</hi> Path, for there are men of wit</l>
            <l>To make you shevv vvher Vertue dwells, a houſe for harbour fit.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:21003:7"/>
            <l> From thence there lies a crooked vvay not eaſie to be founde</l>
            <l>Without a guide and fellovv mate, a harde and rockie grounde:</l>
            <l>VVhere ioyfull <hi>Iustice</hi> ſitts in ſeate and avvefull rule doth beare,</l>
            <l>A happie man is he that can diſpatch and ſoiourne theare.</l>
            <l>The iourney is not farre from that vvhere <hi>Fortitudo</hi> dvvells,</l>
            <l>A famous Dame that all the reſt in courage ſtoute excells.</l>
            <l>Where vvhen thou happen to ariue, be Bolde and neuer blushe:</l>
            <l>For there, there can no cruell care thy minde or carkas crushe.</l>
            <l>When thou vvith theſe acquainted art, to <hi>Temperance</hi> take thy vvay,</l>
            <l>And do vvith hir as fartheſt place of trauaile make thy ſtay.</l>
            <l>For she vvill ſo thy doings guide and in ſuch modeſt vviſe</l>
            <l>Applie hir care to thy behoofe as beſt she can deuiſe.</l>
            <l>She vvill thoſe luring Pleaſures pinche, and ſauſe their ſugred taſt.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:21003:7"/>
            <l> VVith ſovver ſops for thine auaile, as thou shalte ſay at laſt:</l>
            <l>Thrice happie I that founde a guide to enter in this path,</l>
            <l>That to ſo good and bleſſed porte my feete conducted hath.</l>
            <l>Then loke thou backe from whence thou camſt and meaſure vvith thine eyes</l>
            <l>Hovv hard a vvay from <hi>Prudence</hi> to the lodge of <hi>Temperance</hi> lies.</l>
            <l>This, this aſſured is the meane to maiſter Monſtrous Syn,</l>
            <l>And conquere Vice, that by report this Tovvne of late did vvyn.</l>
            <l>March on, let <hi>Mancine</hi> be your guide, if he the banner beare</l>
            <l>And ſtately ſtanderde in the fielde, you nede not ſtande in feare:</l>
            <l>For he ſo vviſely vvill prouide and deale in ery caſe,</l>
            <l>As if that Ladie Vertue vvere there preſt hir ſelfe in place.</l>
            <l>For eu'ry vice a Vertue he vvell furnisht hath in fielde,</l>
            <l>For euery ſinne a countermate to force the Foe to yelde.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:21003:8"/>
            <l>So that though Syn vvere <hi>Hydralike</hi> and head of head did ſpring,</l>
            <l>Yet Vertue should the Conqueſt gaine, and Vice to bondage bring. <note place="margin">The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>queſt of Sinne.</note>
            </l>
            <l>Syn shall be ſubiect had in holde, the Conqueſt shal be none</l>
            <l>VVhoſe great report of late yſpread and rashly ſo vvas blowne.</l>
            <l>Then (Reader) thou beholding art and muſt of force confeſſe</l>
            <l>Thy ſelfe in debt to him that did this perfite Path addreſſe:</l>
            <l>A meane to come vvhere Vertue ſitts in pompe and princely Cell,</l>
            <l>And teacheth men the vvay to liue and waſte their ages vvell.</l>
            <l>And thus with ſute for pardon for this long diſcourſe of mine,</l>
            <l>My tale doth ende, my boke begins which (Reader) shal be thine.</l>
            <l>Reade right, and deeme by due deſerte, miſlike not ere thou ſee</l>
            <l>VVhat is the ende of this diſcourſe that here I giue to thee.</l>
            <l>If nought but Vertue be containde within this Treatiſe, then<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </l>
            <pb facs="tcp:21003:8"/>
            <l>I hope thou vvilt not iudge amiſſe, but thanke my friendly pen,</l>
            <l>That did as vvell for profit as for pleaſure this deuiſe:</l>
            <l>No more, adieu, to reading fall of Vertue as it lies.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>George Turberuyle.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>Iames Sandforde in praiſe of the Tranſlater.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>IF warlike wightes for noble deedes earſt don</l>
               <l>Haue in rewarde and guerdon duely won</l>
               <l>Immortall fame, renowne and glorie aye</l>
               <l>not to decaye:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What then ſhall ſuch deſerue that ſet in ſight</l>
               <l>Things long time hid, in bringing darke to light?</l>
               <l>Shall they not reape of their good ſowen ſeede,</l>
               <l>and haue their meede?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In warre and Peace Minerua beares the ſtroke,</l>
               <l>To Science all the dore ſhe doth vnloke:</l>
               <l>Great is hir force in all the worlde wide</l>
               <l>on euery ſide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Great force hath mightie Mars in fight and fielde,</l>
               <l>Much more Minerua hath, whoſe learned ſhielde</l>
               <l>Doth ſence in warre and peace the publik wealth</l>
               <l>ſauing hir health.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:9"/>
               <l>Who ſo learned Mineruas ſchoole frequent,</l>
               <l>And haue their youthfull yeares in ſtudie ſpent</l>
               <l>Deſerues immortall praiſe and fame to gaine</l>
               <l>for taken paine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then worthie of rewarde is Turberuyle</l>
               <l>Whoſe painfull penne hath thus to Engliſhe ſtyle</l>
               <l>Conuerted learned Mancinus Latine Muſe</l>
               <l>for men to vſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Herein is briefly tolde what Vertue is,</l>
               <l>What life we ought to leade, what leades amiſſe</l>
               <l>A worke of price hath Turberuile tranſpoſde</l>
               <l>and here diſcloſde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Therfore of God and man he well deſcrues:</l>
               <l>For God hath Vertue made, and man it ſerues</l>
               <l>To frame his life: commende the writers pen</l>
               <l>thou Reader then.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>Tutto per il meglio.</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:21003:9"/>
            <head>A plaine Path to perfect <hi>Vertue, deuiſed &amp; found out</hi> by Dominik Mancinus, <hi>a Latine Poet.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Induction to the Treatiſe folowing.</head>
               <l>FIrſt mightie God did make the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and ſandie ſoyle below,</l>
               <l>And did the Elements in place, and ſetled ſeates beſtow:</l>
               <l>The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> next he deckt with gleming ſtars the heauens face on hie,</l>
               <l>With graſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d was trimly tirde and hues of euery die.</l>
               <l>Vnto the fethred Fowles the Ayre he graunted for their home,</l>
               <l>With fiſh he filde the flapping floods and byd them there to rome.</l>
               <l>Then laſt of all he ſhapte a man full like himſelfe to ſée,</l>
               <l>And made all liuing earthly things his humble thrall to bée.</l>
               <l>With Reaſons vſe endued him ek<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, wherby he might be ſéene</l>
               <l>To differ from the brutiſh beaſts and ſauage creatures cléene.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:10"/>
               <l> Then Man poſſeſſing Reaſon, and infeft with wiſedomes lore,</l>
               <l>Began to beate his braines about vnknowne things before.</l>
               <l>Who, for he did forepaſſed things to preſent matters caſt,</l>
               <l>For certaine ſaw the afterclaps and what would chaunce at laſt.</l>
               <l>And ſo p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uiding for the worſt that might by happe ariſe,</l>
               <l>(Well worthie as he was) he gat to be accompted wiſe.</l>
               <l>And that ſelfe Reaſon eake it was that many leagues did make</l>
               <l>And forced flocks of folke to ioyne for aide and friendſhips ſake.</l>
               <l>It cauſ'd the people to obey thoſe wights that rulers were,</l>
               <l>And (after Cities once were raiſ'd) of Lawes to ſtande in feare.</l>
               <l>It bred vnto the childe the zeale and fathers friendly loue,</l>
               <l>And to the reſt that were allide as Nature did behoue.</l>
               <l>And thence it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes that parents haue of them ſuch carking care,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:10"/>
               <l> And thence that children reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſuch as them begot and bare.</l>
               <l>This Reaſon wills that one good turn ſhould aſke an other aye:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd bids that we at néede ſhould helpe our friends the beſt we may:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wixt people ſhe and princely kings both league and truce doth knit,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd makes a loue twixt ſuch as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer were acquainted yit.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd they on whome aboue the reſt God hath beſtowde this gift,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore readie are to ſhew good will and for their friends to ſhift.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o Curteſie twixt man and man confirmed was and gat</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> greater force, by iuſtice ſo their Empires grew to ſtate,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d Kingly more became to them in <hi>Caeſars</hi> roome that ſate.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſides from out this Reaſon in the minds of men there grewe,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> gréedie zeale the ſecrete parts of euery thing to view.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bulte and ſift ſo long about <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pith earneſt care of minde</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:11"/>
               <l> Vntill they mought in e'ry thing the trouth and falſhode finde.</l>
               <l>Which when they had by Reſon fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, this Reaſon gaue them eke</l>
               <l>A feruent loue vnto the thing which they before did ſeke.</l>
               <l>For in good faith no pleaſure is ſo great vnto a man</l>
               <l>As, what in ery caſe is beſt, to iudge and throughly ſcan.</l>
               <l>Which makes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mind ful many time once hauing founde the trouth,</l>
               <l>To flée for any daungers dread it is excéeding loth.</l>
               <l>No churliſhe chaunce, no painful toil the valiant minde ſubdues:</l>
               <l>Ne to mainteine the right it will a preſent death refuſe.</l>
               <l>And thence the branch of Vertue that high Courage cleaped is</l>
               <l>Procéeded, that protector is and guide to ſimplenis.</l>
               <l>Of Reaſon eake the ſlenderſt part we muſt not thinke to bée</l>
               <l>That which doth gyue vs ſuch deligh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> on faireſt things to ſée.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:11"/>
               <l> For only man perceiues and viewes by wit and wilie brayne</l>
               <l>What order is in ery thing, what beautie eke doth raygne,</l>
               <l>And handſomneſſe in Natures frame<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which makes the wittie wight</l>
               <l>When he beholds this worldes forme and hath his ſhape in ſight,</l>
               <l>Thus ſoftly to himſelfe to ſay: how much more beautie might</l>
               <l>Be ſéene in things, if we our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners would conforme a right?</l>
               <l>Wherfore the wiſe mans only carck his maners is to frame</l>
               <l>Vnto the paterne of the things, and make his minde the ſame</l>
               <l>And like in beauties comely ſhewe vnto the things he viewes.</l>
               <l>And this is it that makes him ſhunne, the euill, and quite refuſe</l>
               <l>To ſpot his minde with filthy freakes but to beware and wiſe,</l>
               <l>And flée exceſſe in all his déedes, and let no oddes ariſe</l>
               <l>In ought he vndertakes to do, but deale in euery caſe</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:12"/>
               <l> In ſorte there may no want be foun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> at all of time and place,</l>
               <l>And this doth Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perance take his roo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> within the mindes of men,</l>
               <l>Which fourthly here I minde to tou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and laſt of all with pen.</l>
               <l>Theſe braunches foure, &amp; vertues ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> doth Honeſtie compriſe:</l>
               <l>Which all vnto the vſe of Man from Reaſons roote do riſe.</l>
               <l>And Reaſon from the mightie God and Prince of Princes came,</l>
               <l>But common ſort of ſimple men for Nature terme the ſame.</l>
               <l>But (gentle Reader) take the choyſe and ſay as likes thée beſt,</l>
               <l>Or that it is dame Natures gift, or Gods if ſo thou liſt.</l>
               <l>This I will vndertake of theſe diſtinctly to entreate:</l>
               <l>But firſt of all I thinke it méete the Wiſe man haue his ſeate.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:12"/>
               <head>Of Prudence.</head>
               <l>THe fyrſt and chiefeſt point of that which Honeſtie is hight</l>
               <l>Is falſhode to diſcerne from trouth, the yll from good and right.</l>
               <l>And this ſo paſſing well agrées vnto the kinde of man,</l>
               <l>As nothing more beſéemes than that, nor nothing lightly can.</l>
               <l>For euery man hath ſuch deſire to learne and come to ſkill,</l>
               <l>As nothing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their knowledge ſhould be hidden by their will.</l>
               <l>With gréedie care man pondreth all, and paiſeth in his minde:</l>
               <l>To erre or be deceiued he thinkes it fowle againſt his kinde.</l>
               <l>But he is wiſe that warely waites and ſiftes the matter ſo</l>
               <l>As all his trauaile tends to this what Honeſti's to know.</l>
               <l>To th'ende to put the ſame in v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e. which beſt agrées with that.</l>
               <l>But no man can diſcerne it we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, nor recken what is what:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:13"/>
               <l> But he that meaſures out the ſame accordyng to his kinde</l>
               <l>In euery poynt, and Reaſon takes for Iudge the right to finde.</l>
               <l>A wiſe man will not euer déeme thoſe things to be the beſt</l>
               <l>Which other men allow and iudge farre better than the reſt:</l>
               <l>But ſuch as ſéeme vnto hymſelfe well worthie of the price.</l>
               <l>But certes naytheleſſe he muſt beware in any wiſe</l>
               <l>That Reaſon rule his wittie doome, let Sence obey and yilde</l>
               <l>To Reaſon, as vnto his bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter doth a thrall or childe.</l>
               <l>But that you may haue knowledge of the right with leſſer paine,</l>
               <l>Here orderly eche thing enſues to make the matter plaine.</l>
               <l>Wherfore at firſt who ſo doth ſéeke to haue that Honeſtie,</l>
               <l>Muſt make accompt in all his life two ſpeciall things to flie.</l>
               <l>The one thing is to thinke he k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>es not that which he in dede,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:13"/>
               <l>Is ſkilleſſe of: he muſt not put the thing within his créede</l>
               <l>Wherof he ſtands not well aſſurde, affying ouermuch</l>
               <l>Vpon his owne deuiſe and wit as though there were no ſuch.</l>
               <l>For many things do hidden lie in darke and hollow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en,</l>
               <l>Which is not to attaine with eaſe allowde the wyſeſt men.</l>
               <l>To ſuch allow no light beliefe, beware of raſhe conſent:</l>
               <l>For feare within a litle ſpace thou happen to repent.</l>
               <l>There néedefull will it be to vſe a diligence and care,</l>
               <l>And proceſſe eke of time to know what kinde of things they are.</l>
               <l>And peraduenture we ſhall be compelde for ſafeties ſake,</l>
               <l>To ſéeke a mayſter to inſtruct what way is beſt to take.</l>
               <l>In ſundry things Experience eke will very much auayle</l>
               <l>And counſell of a friende, that will his friende for nothing fayle.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:14"/>
               <l> In doubtfull cauſes ſée thou ſéeke the trouth of either part,</l>
               <l>That howſoere the matter fall, thou mayſt auoide the ſmart.</l>
               <l>'Tis not ſufficient on the one ſide parcially to ſpeake,</l>
               <l>And for to leaue the other part both lame and ouer weake.</l>
               <l>Nor is he to be compted wiſe that warely watcheth aye</l>
               <l>The ſtingyng Adders téeth alone: for of the taile (they ſay)</l>
               <l>And iawes he ſhould beware alike, for either poiſons ſore.</l>
               <l>So do, as that thou mayſt not ſay I thought not this before.</l>
               <l>For why it is a ſhamefull worde for any man to vſe:</l>
               <l>Nor let it thée beguile that doth full many men abuſe,</l>
               <l>That whatſoeuer thing they do preſume or take in hande,</l>
               <l>They thinke it altogether with right and honeſtie to ſtande.</l>
               <l>And whilſte they thus to flattring of themſelues addicted are,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:14"/>
               <l> And ſeruantes to their errours blinde: they deme their wits ſo farre</l>
               <l>To paſſe, that nothing may without their craftie compaſſe lie,</l>
               <l>No Reaſon can preuaile to cauſe them lay their fanſies by.</l>
               <l>No arte can force them to forgo the thing they once maintaine,</l>
               <l>They think their iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t better far than Reaſon neuer ſo plaine:</l>
               <l>As fathers ouer tender of their children, vſe to praiſe</l>
               <l>Their yll demeanor thinking that in them all reaſon ſtayes.</l>
               <l>As when a Caruer cutts a piece or Poet makes a boke,</l>
               <l>They take diſdaine on <hi>Phydeas</hi> worke or feates of warre to loke:</l>
               <l>So theſe their owne commende &amp; like, and with a ſcornefull browe</l>
               <l>Condemne an other mans deuiſe that wiſedome would allow.</l>
               <l>And all bicauſe the loue of that themſelues do take in hands</l>
               <l>Doth bleare their eies, &amp; makes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> none with them in credite ſtands.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:15"/>
               <l> But that they loue themſelues to wel: looke what they do poſſeſſe</l>
               <l>Is orient perle, and glittering golde, all other mens are leſſe</l>
               <l>To be accompted than the filth that in the chanell lies:</l>
               <l>With theſe is Reaſon quite exilde, theſe right and trouth deſpiſe,</l>
               <l>They litle differ from the dumbe and ſauage beaſtly ſect.</l>
               <l>Who ſo the things that common are by Nature, doth reiect,</l>
               <l>And grudgeth ſore to giue the ſame, what? can we déeme that hée</l>
               <l>Will ſhare of any worldly traſhe his proper goodes that bée?</l>
               <l>But yf ſo thou by Fortune chaunce to erre in thys reſpect,</l>
               <l>As of thy ſelfe to make to much, and others to neglect:</l>
               <l>Then mark thou wel with hedeful eye what holy men and graue</l>
               <l>Do holde for good, and thinke it fit for thée the ſame to haue.</l>
               <l>For many looking eyes by daye a great deale more can marke</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:15"/>
               <l> Than can one blynded eye alone diſcerne or iudge by darke.</l>
               <l>And when thou haſt with good aduiſe thy purpoſe throughly ſcande,</l>
               <l>Abandon all delayes, and take with ſpéede thy things in hande.</l>
               <l>A number are ſo lumpiſh and of ſuch a leaden kinde,</l>
               <l>As, though they neuer way ſo much the vertues in their minde,</l>
               <l>Yet are not to be compted wiſe: for why they leaue vndone</l>
               <l>That part which is the chief of all where wiſedome is begon.</l>
               <l>Euen ſo the gréene and gallant boughs vpon the trée do bud,</l>
               <l>But if they bring not forth their fruite in time, it doth no good.</l>
               <l>Euen ſo the Souldiers march in field, and muſter in aray,</l>
               <l>But neuer come to handie cuffes to bring the ſpoyle away.</l>
               <l>Euen ſo into the fallowde fields in vaine the ſeede is throwne,</l>
               <l>Vnleſſe with ſithe thou ſheare it down when it to head is growne.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:16"/>
               <l> For chiefeſt praiſe that vertue brings in Act conſiſteth aye:</l>
               <l>And to conſult, and nought to do is litle worth they ſay.</l>
               <l>But yet he wants not vertues praiſe but is commended too,</l>
               <l>That beates his braines about the beſt although he can not doo</l>
               <l>Nor put in vre his purpoſ'd plat: For ſickneſſe hinders ſome,</l>
               <l>And makes that they can neuer to their hoped purpoſe come.</l>
               <l>Philoſophers do well deſerue both fame and praiſe to gayne,</l>
               <l>Who by their writing well to ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues trauaile vs to traine.</l>
               <l>There is an other vice beſide, which is, long time to ſpende</l>
               <l>With ouer earneſt ſtudie in ſuch things as in the ende</l>
               <l>Are rough, and not to be attainde: for ſundry things are ſuch</l>
               <l>And ſo profounde, as nought at all they profite ſéeme to touche.</l>
               <l>For to the ende they nought auaile or profit any whit</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:16"/>
               <l> To bettring of our liues, although they vexe vs day and night.</l>
               <l>Or if they mought do any good<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or ayde vs to attaine</l>
               <l>The ſcope it ſelfe: yet all the ſame I compte to be more vaine</l>
               <l>And leſſe auailing than the ende if it be ſought alone.</l>
               <l>What profit comes there by the ſearch of mouing ſtarres? thou foole</l>
               <l>To learne the things, and cauſe therof why doſte thou go to ſchoole?</l>
               <l>Why couetſt thou with earneſt carke ſo many artes to know?</l>
               <l>Or haue the ſkill how Countreys are diſpoſed in arow?</l>
               <l>Why doſt thou ioy and long ſo ſore by craft and wilie witte</l>
               <l>The ſubtile Sophiſter to paſſe concluſions falſe to knit?</l>
               <l>Or with a ſwéete perſuading voice and pleaſant proceſſe tolde</l>
               <l>Why doſte thou couete ſo the poore and ſimple eares to holde?</l>
               <l>If wyſe thou be, no whit at all of theſe thou ſtandſt in néede,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:17"/>
               <l> More plaine and ſimple is it farre that thou ſhouldſt learne in déede:</l>
               <l>Do learne the way both well to liue and well to die the death,</l>
               <l>Theſe two alone are ours: we liue and looſe at length our breath.</l>
               <l>A meane and ſlender ſtudie will inſtruct vs well ynowe,</l>
               <l>It is an eaſie knacke the meane to either of both to knowe.</l>
               <l>Wherfore at firſt behouefull is to wit the thing that may</l>
               <l>Make happie thée, and in thy breaſt let it full firmely ſtay.</l>
               <l>And therwith learn the middle meane and path that thither lies,</l>
               <l>Which when thou haſt once paſed in, perſiſt in any wiſe.</l>
               <l>For many all their liues and dayes in learning it do waſt,</l>
               <l>But haue no gréedie minde or will to trauaile on at laſt.</l>
               <l>What vailes to practiſe how to know the way, and there to reſt? which when thou knowſt thy ſhame is far more ſhameful than the reſt</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:17"/>
               <l> That neuer wiſt the way to good wilte thou the path diſplay</l>
               <l>To other men, and wilt meanewhile thy ſelfe go runne aſtray?</l>
               <l>Wilt thou aduiſe by counſell good another man to that</l>
               <l>Which y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> doſt leue vntoucht, as though thou knewſt not what were what?</l>
               <l>How vaine a practiſe is't the dayes and nights at worke t'haue watcht,</l>
               <l>And by thy toile to profite nought when matters are diſpatcht?</l>
               <l>In vaine good faith our labour is and time miſpent full ſore,</l>
               <l>Vnleſſe the déede do folow that which was conceiude before.</l>
               <l>Then ſince the Act is perfite ende of ſtudie, more deſir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>To work with wiſedom, than to learn to knowledge to aſpire.</l>
               <l>And therfore not without a cauſe the Souldier ſtoute did ſcorne</l>
               <l>Philoſophers that all their liues in babling ſchooles haue worne.</l>
               <l>For ſayes the Souldier (maſter Sage) I pray you tell me, what</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:18"/>
               <l> Auayles it you to crie ſo loude and chiding wiſe to chat?</l>
               <l>You braule from dawning vnto darke from riſing Sunne to night,</l>
               <l>Yet neuer agrée: one flatte affirmes an other denies it quight.</l>
               <l>The wiſe man anſwered, (O my ſon) we ſéeke that Vertue (man)</l>
               <l>Which none with erneſt ſtudy inough coulde euer ſéeke or can.</l>
               <l>The Souldier ſmylde, what haſt (quod he) thy head with heares ſo gray</l>
               <l>And haſt not yet to Vertue founde the readie path and way?</l>
               <l>Why? whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then wilt thou vſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame? what? haſt thou any hope</l>
               <l>To practiſe it in <hi>Plutos</hi> court? or there to haue ſuch ſcope?</l>
               <l>Wherfore do learne as much as thou mayſt put in preſent vre,</l>
               <l>And hauing learnde to fall vnto the Acte it ſelfe be ſure.</l>
               <l>It lies not hid, but vnto ſuch as reache with earneſt fiſt</l>
               <l>It offers to be had, eche man may catche it if he liſt.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:18"/>
               <l> Beſides a parte of Prudence is an Order to obſerue</l>
               <l>In doing things, from which a wiſe man neuer ought to ſwerue.</l>
               <l>Firſt way thou wel the greteſt things and matters moſt of weight,</l>
               <l>And then do place in ſeconde roome more leſſer things and light.</l>
               <l>It is no reaſon thou refuſe thy wife and babes, to haue</l>
               <l>A greater carke of plowing boy and of thy houſholde ſlaue.</l>
               <l>Ne lawfull is't thy life to way but litle, or thy health,</l>
               <l>Whilſt like a gréedie man thou goeſt about to hoorde vp wealth.</l>
               <l>Looſe not thy ſoule (I pray thée) whilſt thou ſéeke for bodies cure:</l>
               <l>For why? more precious is the ſoule, the body more impure.</l>
               <l>Wherof ſhould man accompt ſo much, as that he ſhoulde meane while</l>
               <l>Neglect his ſoule, in whoſe regarde all treaſure is but vile?</l>
               <l>What mad man would deſire in earth to liue a litle ſpace,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:19"/>
               <l> And by the ſame in endleſſe death to haue a laſting place?</l>
               <l>And ſure if due reſpect be had to wordles and endleſſe yeares,</l>
               <l>Thy life and age a moment then vnto thine eye appeares.</l>
               <l>Haue aye regarde that him to whom thou moſt indebted art</l>
               <l>Thou recompence in ampleſt wiſe: but chiefly yet in heart</l>
               <l>And all before haue God in thought. for mindfull though thou be</l>
               <l>In all reſpects beſide, yet all is nothing worth if he</l>
               <l>Be neuer minded but forgot. Haue not regard alone</l>
               <l>Of preſent time, but what thy ſtate ſhall be when life is gone.</l>
               <l>What more pertaines vnto a man than in his minde to way</l>
               <l>The afterclaps that if befall may hurte an other day?</l>
               <l>But doubtleſſe death and life againe ſhall happen after this:</l>
               <l>Which either vs ſhall pay with paines or bring to better blis.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:19"/>
               <l> And that which comes in after time no certaine limites hath,</l>
               <l>And ſo either endleſſe is the ioy or laſting is the wrath.</l>
               <l>But as this life is ſhadow like, and blaſt of winde to ſée,</l>
               <l>Euen ſo the good or euils ſhe giues too ſhort and ſlipper bée.</l>
               <l>This place alone for pardon ſerues whilſte we in earth do liue,</l>
               <l>That other life with rigour right to euery man will giue.</l>
               <l>More better 'tis ſome pleaſant paines to bide and ſuffer here,</l>
               <l>Than torment neuer ſtinting in the helliſhe fire to beare.</l>
               <l>That yoke is eaſie to the necke that with good will is worne,</l>
               <l>But grieuous is the burden that vnwillingly is borne.</l>
               <l>Here <hi>CHRIST</hi> with phyſike goes about our pained limmes to heale,</l>
               <l>But there with dreadfull iudges face that gaſtly God will deale.</l>
               <l>Accompt not that of any price or woorth purſute to bée,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:20"/>
               <l> Which paſſeth by in litle ſpace: let that be ſought of thée,</l>
               <l>Which long will laſt in ſteady ſtay not fléeing by and by.</l>
               <l>Nor let that filthie fading traſhe within thy coffer lye</l>
               <l>That with a turne of hande is reft not able aide to giue</l>
               <l>In time of néede, vnable wares the owner to relieue.</l>
               <l>By Iuſtice meaſure all thy déedes, nor though thou happen to</l>
               <l>Be matcht with wicked wights, do not thy woonted trade forgo,</l>
               <l>But kéepe thée as thou wert before let Iuſtice aye be one,</l>
               <l>Although thou change as time require, the way that thou haſt gone.</l>
               <l>For often double is the path that to one ende doth lye,</l>
               <l>And one perhaps is now ſhut vp, when the other way is hie.</l>
               <l>Euen as the hand now ſtretcheth fort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it ſelfe by ioyntes awide</l>
               <l>And then becomes a fiſt againe, yet one ſelfe hande doth bide:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:20"/>
               <l> So will a wiſe man aye be iuſt and euer at a ſtay:</l>
               <l>Although he chaunge his countenance according to the day.</l>
               <l>I would not haue thée light as winde, but euen as time ſhall ſerue.</l>
               <l>And as the caſe requires, be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant ſtill and neuer ſwerue</l>
               <l>But not to hard, or to ſeuere, nor ouer haſtily</l>
               <l>Beleue thou euery tale that goes or credite euery lye.</l>
               <l>He both deceiues him ſelfe, and eake beguiles an other that</l>
               <l>Doth lende beleuing eare to euery man that loues to chat.</l>
               <l>A wittie man ſhould both abhorre: for often times hath bene</l>
               <l>The thyng that fained was to ſight and that which men would wéene</l>
               <l>And take for truth hath fallen out a matter nothing ſo:</l>
               <l>How often times doth truth in cloke of fained falſhode go?</l>
               <l>And falſhode eke how often hath it lurkt to open ſight</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:21"/>
               <l> In ſhade and countnance of a truth, not euer lies are dight</l>
               <l>Or beare their proper ſhapes and hues: and ſundry times we ſee</l>
               <l>That mere ſimplicitie is thought a déepe deceyt to bée.</l>
               <l>And as the flattering fawning gueſt a friendly face doth weare:</l>
               <l>So he that counſels well ſomtime a hatefull heart doth beare.</l>
               <l>Of matters doubtfull giue no doome or certaine iudgement, but</l>
               <l>So place your words as you the caſe ſtill in ſuſpence may put.</l>
               <l>When ought thou mind to take in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d firſt ponder well in thought</l>
               <l>How great it is, and what may hap when things ar throughly wrought.</l>
               <l>If that thou minde to ſet vpon require no earneſt haſt,</l>
               <l>Attempt it not with retchleſſe hande, nor do it ouer faſt.</l>
               <l>Defer the thing wherof you doubt vntil ſuch time you may</l>
               <l>Haue certaine knowledge what it is: No damage comes by ſtay.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:21"/>
               <l> Beſide, what ſo thou ſurely knowſt vnrightfully begoon,</l>
               <l>Thou oughtſt of duetie to forgo and leaue it quite vndoon.</l>
               <l>And if ſuſpition chaunce to grow within thy doubtfull breaſt,</l>
               <l>Do ſhift it of: but ſtill beware thou be not then oppreſt.</l>
               <l>Thou muſt in al thy talke what right and reaſon is, aduiſe,</l>
               <l>Or ſéeke it out at leaſt: for that in couert oft it lies.</l>
               <l>Thou muſt vnto the ſimple ſort what Honeſt is declare:</l>
               <l>And ſhew the way: but thoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtraine that at commaundement are.</l>
               <l>And eke no ſlender part of praiſe and vertue lightes on thée</l>
               <l>If thou with comfort ſolace thoſe in griping griefs that bée.</l>
               <l>The wight that well deſerueth praiſe not ouermuch commende:</l>
               <l>Nor ouer ſharply do controll the man that doth offende:</l>
               <l>For he of flatterie bides the taint that to much praiſe beſtowes:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:22"/>
               <l> And he that too much doth reproue a naughtie tongue of thoſe</l>
               <l>That hear his talk, is thought to haue. A greater care thou muſt</l>
               <l>Haue of a truth than of a friende, be true and euer iuſt.</l>
               <l>Before thou promiſe waigh thy welth, and what thou haſt in ſtore:</l>
               <l>And hauing promiſ'd, kepe thy touch, and fully rid thy ſcore.</l>
               <l>Looke backe vpon the paſſed time, the future date forſee,</l>
               <l>That like a wittie man thou maiſt do things that néedefull bée.</l>
               <l>Foreſcan the profite and the paine that may enſue or ere</l>
               <l>Thou do attempt, to thende thou maiſt miſſehaps the better beare.</l>
               <l>Thou ſhalt not euer worke and toyle, ſometime from trauaile blin,</l>
               <l>And purchaſe quiet to the minde that it may reſt within.</l>
               <l>But in that vacant leyſure time apply thou not thy paunch,</l>
               <l>But with good learnings dayntie cates thy gaping hunger ſtaunch.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:22"/>
               <l> Flée Idleneſſe when ſo vnto thy néedefull reſt thou go,</l>
               <l>And practiſe then ſome godly thought within thy breaſt below:</l>
               <l>Or elſe thy matters left vndone do ponder in thy braine:</l>
               <l>For ſure the quiete minde can then iudge matters paſſing plaine.</l>
               <l>It forwarde ſetts the matter ſlackt, it doubtfull things conuayes:</l>
               <l>The hard it ſoftneth, maketh plaine the rough and ragged wayes.</l>
               <l>Vnoccupied it not beſéemes the wiſe mans witts to bée:</l>
               <l>Although his hande hath layde aſide his working tooles, yet hée</l>
               <l>In minde muſt practiſe ſomwhat ſtill. Haue not ſo great a carke</l>
               <l>To note how other men offende, thine owne offenſes marke.</l>
               <l>Loue aye to learne, but not to force of whome thou takſte the ſkill,</l>
               <l>Let it ſuffiſe thée to haue learnde, let that content thy will.</l>
               <l>Wexe ware and wiſe by others déedes, for oftentimes (they ſay)</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:23"/>
               <l> Attaine the ſkill of matters great by little things we may.</l>
               <l>What euery man will after be the tender age doth ſhowe:</l>
               <l>And of the life that is to come by one dayes ſight we know.</l>
               <l>Let not the Author of a worde or déede thée ſtirre or moue,</l>
               <l>But as the thing it ſelfe requires and is for thy behoue.</l>
               <l>Nor like not with thy ſelfe too well for that a number haue</l>
               <l>A good conceite of thée: but learne where they be wiſe and graue</l>
               <l>That do commende thy doings ſo. Enſerch with buſie care</l>
               <l>To know ſuch things, which lawfully to be enſearched are:</l>
               <l>Learn that which law permits to lern, and wiſh to haue the thing</l>
               <l>Which being wiſht for openly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> no ſhame at all may bring.</l>
               <l>Beware of ouerloftie ſtall where feare it is to ſtande,</l>
               <l>Or whence to come great daunger is. Take euer that in hande,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:23"/>
               <l> And theron beate thy buſie braine that bréedes thée quiete reſt.</l>
               <l>Some things there are which if y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſéeke to get, thou ſhalt be geſt</l>
               <l>Bothe wiſe to be and well allowde: but then thou muſt beware</l>
               <l>When that thou haſt attainde inough to holde thy hande with care.</l>
               <l>When once thou gotten haſt the welth that may ſupplie thy want,</l>
               <l>The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeke for that for which thou liu'ſt, for which thy God did graunt</l>
               <l>Thée here to waſt thy many dayes. Thou muſt not be a ſlaue</l>
               <l>Vnto thy traſhe and rotten pelfe, but them thy vaſſals haue.</l>
               <l>Looke what thou wouldſt not do if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man did thée beholde,</l>
               <l>That do not when thou art alone: nor be nowhyt more bolde</l>
               <l>Bycauſe no witneſſe lookes vpon and viewes thy déedes the while.</l>
               <l>When Fortune w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hir laughing brows on thée begyns to ſmile,</l>
               <l>Then follow counſell moſt of all, let wiſedome be thy guide.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:24"/>
               <l> For as the féete of him that ſtandes vpon the yſe will ſlide:</l>
               <l>So wyll the wights that happie are the golden meane forget,</l>
               <l>And can not ſtay where Reaſon wills that they their footing ſet.</l>
               <l>Nor yet among the ſtormie ſhowres the Barke doth more lament</l>
               <l>When it amid the ſeas doth ſtand in perill to be rent,</l>
               <l>Than Reaſon in proſperitie the happie man bewailes.</l>
               <l>Wherfore when that a pleaſant gale doth blow thy bleſſed ſailes</l>
               <l>Runne not at randon after luſt, but ſéeke the ſafeſt ſeate.</l>
               <l>Oft times in calme and quiete ſeas when no fell windes do beate,</l>
               <l>Beneath the water lies the rock and cruell cruſhing ſtone,</l>
               <l>And oft by them with rented ribbs the ſhaken ſhip doth grone.</l>
               <l>Whilſt ſundry times y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bark doth bear his full and ſtrouting ſailes,</l>
               <l>A ſodaine ſhowre with furious blaſt his pride and courage quailes.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:24"/>
               <l> None mindes to trap thée in the ſnare that vſeth threatning ſtile,</l>
               <l>But by his churliſh checks doth make thée héedefull more the while.</l>
               <l>The chéerefull looke and freindly face, the eye with wanton winke</l>
               <l>Beguiles vs moſt: with ſyrops ſwéete we poiſon oft do drinke.</l>
               <l>So ſmiling fortune many men by cuſtome doth intrap,</l>
               <l>Whom frowning to ſubdue before ſhe neuer had the hap.</l>
               <l>And thus is Prudence here diſplayde, of Iuſtice next we muſt</l>
               <l>Intreate, that knits the wordle in loue and knot of friendly truſt.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Iuſtice.</head>
               <l>THis Iuſtice is a certaine knot of Nature, and a band</l>
               <l>That wylls vs vnto many that we lende our helping hand.</l>
               <l>So perfite and ſo ſure a league twixt man and man it knitts,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:25"/>
               <l> As by this onely Iuſtice meanes mankinde in ſafetie ſitts.</l>
               <l>Demaunde not whether that ſhée bids bring profite yea or no:</l>
               <l>For profitable ſure it is how ſo the game doth go.</l>
               <l>The chiefeſt part of Iuſtice is to render honour due</l>
               <l>To God, that gaue vs all, and eke himſelfe on trée to rue.</l>
               <l>Therfore who ſo a Chriſtian longs to be, and haue the name,</l>
               <l>That chiefly he do loue his God is néedefull for the ſame.</l>
               <l>And let him loue him ſo as he may well deſerue agayne</l>
               <l>To be belou'd and fauour fynde. And this he may attayne</l>
               <l>That willingly will hinder none nor damage any man,</l>
               <l>But pleaſure all and profite eke as much as ere he can.</l>
               <l>For ſo is God himſelfe to men, that to no one denies,</l>
               <l>Which liues on earth, the vſe of ſunne though he in wicked wiſe</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:25"/>
               <l> Do leade a vile and beaſtly life and giue himſelfe to luſt.</l>
               <l>Ne yet doth he deſerue at full to be accompted iuſt</l>
               <l>That profits none, nor any wrongs: for Vertue doth require</l>
               <l>A déede wel woorthy praiſe to haue, that's Vertues chiefe deſire,</l>
               <l>She compts it not ynough from yll to haue the hande forborne.</l>
               <l>Ne are we here on earth vnto our priuate profite borne,</l>
               <l>But eche man bound to ſéeke the helpe for others as we may:</l>
               <l>For men were men begot and borne was <hi>Plato</hi> woont to ſay,</l>
               <l>To ayde eche other at néedefull times. but eu'ry man aléeke</l>
               <l>Can neither helpe, nor holpen be: wherfore we muſt go ſéeke</l>
               <l>And compaſſe how to do it beſt. for if by ayde of hande</l>
               <l>Nor Moneys meane thou mayſt aſſiſt or by thy neighbour ſtande:</l>
               <l>Yet do by counſell what thou canſt, relieue him with thy paine.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:26"/>
               <l> Beſide, thou being ſtrong of force the wicked mayſt conſtraine</l>
               <l>To hold their hands from hurting ſuch as ſiellie Creatures are,</l>
               <l>And be a meane that ſimple men may ſcape the ſubtills ſnare.</l>
               <l>Againe, by good aduiſe and réede, by comfort and by checke</l>
               <l>Thou mayſt do pleaſure many times to them that would to wrecke.</l>
               <l>But yet in doing dueties wée muſt caſt a hedefull eye</l>
               <l>To Order, State, and eke Degrée: for Order certainly</l>
               <l>To ery thing doth lende a ſhape and beautie paſſing fine.</l>
               <l>As, firſt to God thy duetie do, then next of all incline</l>
               <l>To profite of thy Countrey ſoyle reſpect thy natiue lande,</l>
               <l>Then children and thy parents deare require thy helping hande.</l>
               <l>And after theſe by blood allide and friends by office woonne:</l>
               <l>Ne yet thou muſt the poore, the ſicke or aged cripple ſhoonne.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:26"/>
               <l> But rather be to pitie mou'd: and eke among the ſame</l>
               <l>If any paſſe in Honeſtie then ſure thou art to blame</l>
               <l>If thoſe thou do not moſt regarde and pitie in thy heart,</l>
               <l>And to their great and heauie néede thy friendly face conuart.</l>
               <l>And they that earſt haue holpen thée are to be holpe againe:</l>
               <l>But then thou muſt remember that thou do it with a gayne.</l>
               <l>Do follow, as <hi>Heſiodus</hi> did will, the fertile fielde</l>
               <l>That to the Ploughman with increaſe the ſcattred ſéede doth yelde.</l>
               <l>But yet thou muſt beware, that whilſt for any one thou ſhift,</l>
               <l>No other man therby thou do from ſeate and ſaddle lift.</l>
               <l>Prouide and wiſely watche beſide leſt whilſt that thou art bent</l>
               <l>To ſhew good nature, wealth do fayle, and then thou rap and rent</l>
               <l>From other men their proper goods. For commonly (they ſay)</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:27"/>
               <l> The waſtfull Bankrupt forceth not from whom he take away,</l>
               <l>When all his ſubſtance is conſumde, then gets he yll report.</l>
               <l>Commit no pillage to augment thy former ſtate and porte:</l>
               <l>No not to gayne a Princes crowne from Iuſtice ſwerue awrye.</l>
               <l>And not alone the iuſt man muſt from force and pillage flye,</l>
               <l>But eake abandon fraude and gile: to Foxes fraude doth long,</l>
               <l>Vnto the noble Lion force, for he is paſſing ſtrong.</l>
               <l>But neither fraude nor force becomes a man in any caſe.</l>
               <l>And ſure is none more deadly than the man that beares a face</l>
               <l>And ſiellie ſhew of ſimple ſhéepe, and is a woulfe within:</l>
               <l>And hath his maners quite againſt the colour of his ſkin.</l>
               <l>And not alone in déede, for oft in woords is wrong: as when</l>
               <l>Thou doſt obiect a fained crime to good and giltleſſe men.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:27"/>
               <l> Pronounce the trouth with tong, &amp; eke defende it euermore,</l>
               <l>In ſort as not by any thing thou ſet a greater ſtore.</l>
               <l>Nor do thou thinke that by a lie thou canſt once falſe thy trouth,</l>
               <l>But that therwith Religion quite is broken, and an othe.</l>
               <l>For though that God for witneſſe be not cited to the bande,</l>
               <l>Yet not the leſſe he aye in place of good recorde doth ſtande.</l>
               <l>And if at any time at all it lawfull be to lie:</l>
               <l>Perhaps it is that trouth may be apparant more therby.</l>
               <l>And he perhaps that ſpeaketh falſe his promiſe to preſerue,</l>
               <l>Perchaunce the ſame for all his lie a pardon doth deſerue.</l>
               <l>So plighted heſt muſt ere be kept as Conſtancie be founde</l>
               <l>In all our words, our promiſes with credite muſt abounde.</l>
               <l>But ſo it happen may ſometime as ſlender is the faulte,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:28"/>
               <l> To breake a promiſe firmely made or with a man to haulte.</l>
               <l>As if I promiſe that to thée that will no profite bréede,</l>
               <l>Or that which more will me annoy than pleaſure thée in déede.</l>
               <l>Duke <hi>Theſeus</hi> coulde haue wiſhed erſt with all his minde and hart</l>
               <l>That <hi>Neptune</hi> wold his promiſe broke when <hi>Hippolite</hi> in cart</l>
               <l>(Vnhappie youth) was drawne about the cruell craggie clife,</l>
               <l>Where he for no deſert of his was reft his honeſt life.</l>
               <l>Let not the Iuſt man blabbe abrode the ſecretes he doth heare,</l>
               <l>Nor in vnlawfull matters let his tongue not dare to ſteare.</l>
               <l>By doubtfull words bréede no debate nor quarell while you liue,</l>
               <l>But rather certaine iudgement in eche thyng demaunded giue,</l>
               <l>Or rather holde thy peace out right, when is no cauſe to chat:</l>
               <l>For often doth the prating tong offende it knowes not what,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:28"/>
               <l> And wrongs it ſelfe, and others too. If thou in common weale</l>
               <l>Do beare an office, and haſt cauſe in ſuch affaires to deale:</l>
               <l>Or hauing ſtore of houſhold folks at home at meale and meate,</l>
               <l>The partie that doth yll deſerue let him be duely beate.</l>
               <l>To be accompted ouermylde, it is no prayſe at all:</l>
               <l>For he that fauours one that doth amiſſe, will marre them all.</l>
               <l>If any do offenſe, and thou be parciall to correct,</l>
               <l>That thou art guiltie of the ſame we may right well ſuſpect.</l>
               <l>The Magiſtrate doth fauour faults that letts a matter ſlippe:</l>
               <l>And too much fauour of the Iudge is called a gentle whippe.</l>
               <l>He marres the multitude, and doth whole Cities bring to ſacke,</l>
               <l>That iuſtly doth not vſe the ſcourge vpon the ſinners backe.</l>
               <l>He quite vndoes them: as the man that flings a fiery brande</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:29"/>
               <l> Into a towne, or gate vnlocks when foes are harde at hande.</l>
               <l>We can not call that Ruler good nor terme him as a King,</l>
               <l>But rather ſuch a one as plague and miſchiefe loues to bring.</l>
               <l>But yet in puniſhment of vice we muſt not Reaſon paſſe:</l>
               <l>To keepe the meane in ery thing is good and euer was.</l>
               <l>When ſo thou takſt the rod in hande then be not to ſeuere,</l>
               <l>As though at other mens diſtreſſe thou glad or ioyfull were:</l>
               <l>But puniſhe ſore againſt thy will as though thou were conſtrainde</l>
               <l>Thertoo, and that thou didſt lament his caſe that ſo is painde.</l>
               <l>Beſide if ſundry ſinne alike and in one poynt offende,</l>
               <l>Releaſe not one, and let the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be in priſon pende.</l>
               <l>Rewarde not theſe with rigor whilſte thou deale with other well:</l>
               <l>I meane of thoſe that all at once of lawe in daunger fell.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:29"/>
               <l> Let like offenſe haue like rewarde: deale not in Fathers wiſe</l>
               <l>With one, and like a cruel foe with tother. Spiders guiſe</l>
               <l>Is to entrap in craftie webbe the litle ſiellie gnat:</l>
               <l>But if there come a hornette huge or waſpe that's weightie fat,</l>
               <l>He cruſheth downe the ſlender twiſt and makes a thorough wayes,</l>
               <l>Whilſt ſiellie flies in hanging netts the ſpitefull Spider ſlayes:</l>
               <l>Euen ſo the poore and miſer man the cruell law doth cruſhe</l>
               <l>If he offende, but welthie wights through tiled trap do ruſhe.</l>
               <l>If any doe thée wrong: let wreake but counteruaile the déede:</l>
               <l>Séeke not to puniſh his offenſe no more than thou haſt néede:</l>
               <l>But if thou quite forgiue the fact and no reuenge doe ſéeke,</l>
               <l>Thou art the iuſter man for that, God thée the more will léeke.</l>
               <l>Vnto thy ſeruants eake thou ſhalt obſerue both law and right,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:30"/>
               <l> Gyue them their due, &amp; looke that they thy Iuſtice doe requight.</l>
               <l>For Nature them our brothers made. ſo that thou muſt ſuppoſe</l>
               <l>That fowly he offends that paſt the bounds of mercy goes.</l>
               <l>If ſo their crimes committed bée too heynous, ryd thy hande</l>
               <l>Of them, or elſe be mercifull: but if the caſe do ſtande</l>
               <l>Vpon ſome ſmall and lyght offenſe, who can foreſée to much?</l>
               <l>Or who can deale with too great ruth if ſo the caſe be ſuch?</l>
               <l>And ſithens we haue thus vnbard the gate of Iuſtice hall,</l>
               <l>We will of Valiance next intreate that yelds to nought at all.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Magnanimitie.</head>
               <l>OF high and noble Courage I that Man confeſſe to bée,</l>
               <l>That in defenſe of honeſt name no daungers dread will flée.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:30"/>
               <l> But willing vndertake to do the hardeſt things of all:</l>
               <l>He feares no man, he dreades no death nor ought that may befall.</l>
               <l>No torment can the Noble minde, no yrefull threates ſubdue,</l>
               <l>But onely ſacred reaſon make him chaunge his will anewe.</l>
               <l>But yet he will not raſhely and in wilfull wiſe deſire</l>
               <l>The perill or the daunger, but as matter ſhall require.</l>
               <l>For ſure more fonde may nothing be, than for a man to put</l>
               <l>His lyfe in daunger, where he mought auoyde without a cut.</l>
               <l>That man is ouer braynſicke madde that ſafe and well at eaſe</l>
               <l>Vpon the riuer, longs to launch amyd the mounting Seas.</l>
               <l>He that his Countrey doth moleſt, or breakes the Common lawes,</l>
               <l>That hym we Valiant ſhold accompt, there is at all no cauſe</l>
               <l>But rather bolde and bedlim beaſt, raſhe and vngodly wight</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:31"/>
               <l> And any other terme that tongue can well deuiſe with ſpite.</l>
               <l>Nor he Couragious that doth ſéeke his owne and priuate gaine:</l>
               <l>But he that in his countreys cauſe doth offer to be ſlaine.</l>
               <l>For ſure there is no praiſe of minde no worthie feate in dede,</l>
               <l>Leſſe it from Iuſtice, and the loue of countrey ſoyle procede.</l>
               <l>Nor leſſe he liue vprightly, and plaine dealing vſe, he can</l>
               <l>Not gaine the name of Fortitude, or of a noble man.</l>
               <l>Let not the tickling brute of thy good déedes thine eyes delight:</l>
               <l>Let it ſuffiſe thée that thou didſt atchieue the ſame aright.</l>
               <l>For Magnanimitie hath aye reſpect of Honeſtie,</l>
               <l>As for reports of giddie heads it forceth not a flie.</l>
               <l>Nor he that doth depende vpon the brute of peoples braine</l>
               <l>Deſerues the name of valiant minde and Courage to attaine:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:31"/>
               <l> But he that coulde for go the thing for which himſelfe doth long,</l>
               <l>That man in dede is valiant, that man is truely ſtrong.</l>
               <l>Who ſo doth ouermuch delight in Titles of his name,</l>
               <l>And with an earneſt ſtudie doth ſéeke out and ſearch the ſame,</l>
               <l>Is too too fonde and childiſh wight: for chiefly doth pertaine</l>
               <l>To valiant Courage to contemne the things that are but vaine</l>
               <l>Which common raſcall much co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend. the baſeſt things deſpiſe,</l>
               <l>The noble minde doth couete that where dread and daunger lies:</l>
               <l>It thinkes that all theſe earthly things are ſubiect vnto him.</l>
               <l>Not all that he doth ſée with eye, or touch with other lim</l>
               <l>But what w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> inwarde mind he viewes for woorthy iewel takes.</l>
               <l>Who ſo doth ſcorne the earth, and of his minde a heauen makes,</l>
               <l>That man I noble déeme to be, that is a worthie wight.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:32"/>
               <l> But how can he be compted great and be of noble might,</l>
               <l>That here belowe in earth doth dwell nor doth aduaunce his head</l>
               <l>Vp to the haughtie things aloft but lies like one were dead?</l>
               <l>Will any man denie that it pertaines to Noble minde</l>
               <l>By vertue to deſerue the ſeate that is to Kings aſſignde?</l>
               <l>Then doubtleſſe he is greater farre that doth deſerue by déede</l>
               <l>A ſeate with mightie God in ſkies on heauenly ioyes to féede.</l>
               <l>Who will denie the man to be of force and famous, that</l>
               <l>By cruell ſiege doth conquer townes and beates the Cities flat?</l>
               <l>Then ſurely he is ſtronger much that by deſert doth gayne</l>
               <l>The ſtately fort of haughtie Heauen with <hi>Ioue</hi> to parte his raigne.</l>
               <l>No toile or tedious trauaile can the valiant man diſmay,</l>
               <l>To cauſe that from his worke begoon he leaue or ſéeme to ſtay:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:32"/>
               <l> So let it loathe thée nought at all at heauen doore to knocke,</l>
               <l>To th'ende the porter may at length the gladſome gate vnlocke.</l>
               <l>The heauenly porter ſcornes of none that beates with willing fiſt:</l>
               <l>Nor any yet that iuſtly crau'd his iuſt demaunde hath myſt.</l>
               <l>Wherfore go too, do neuer leaue thy wearie armes to lifte</l>
               <l>Vnto the ſkies, ſince he at laſt will giue thy hoped gift.</l>
               <l>Thou ſhalt attaine thy ſute at length, ceaſſe not till all be done:</l>
               <l>A worthie crowne is due to him that all the race doth ronne.</l>
               <l>Nor do not thinke the ende to farre, for when thou thinkeſt leaſt</l>
               <l>That thou art there, thou haſt diſpatcht then ſhalt thou be at reaſt.</l>
               <l>The Noble minde is neuer bonde or thrall, but euer frée</l>
               <l>From all offenſe: and fellow loues to God and Right to be.</l>
               <l>Nor doth it ſuffer riot, or vnlawfull luſt to raigne,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:33"/>
               <l> But for to yelde vnto his force the Sences doth conſtraine.</l>
               <l>No greater ſlauerie than to haue thy minde at Vices becke:</l>
               <l>And ſée that Beaſt to ſet his foote vpon thy yoked necke.</l>
               <l>That is a perfite fréedom of the minde, whome to the yoke</l>
               <l>May no alluring pleaſure, or vnlaufull luſt prouoke.</l>
               <l>It meruailes not at any thing vnleſſe it beare a face</l>
               <l>Of Honeſtie, and ſtedfaſt be in one ſelfe roome and place.</l>
               <l>It neuer yeldes to frowarde chaunce but conſtant euer bides:</l>
               <l>And yll aduenture vnder cloke of merie countnance hides.</l>
               <l>For ſure the man of valiant minde doth force of no miſſehap,</l>
               <l>But all good things doth déeme that he within his minde doth wrap.</l>
               <l>And he alone within his minde compriſeth eu'ry thing,</l>
               <l>That day and night doth euer thinke vpon the heauens King.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:33"/>
               <l> He frames his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tnance graue &amp; wiſe, he lookes with boldned browe:</l>
               <l>No hautie language makes him feare or cauſeth him to bowe.</l>
               <l>It doth not well become a man of ſtoute and ſturdie ſtampe,</l>
               <l>To ſtare with ſterne &amp; glowing eyes and Lyonlike to rampe.</l>
               <l>But rather haue a viſage mylde and browe of friendly grace.</l>
               <l>For why a Valiant man in déede not iudged is by face,</l>
               <l>Or by his outward geſture demde: the déede it ſelfe is it</l>
               <l>And mind that makes the Noble man. Thy ſelfe thou muſt not quit</l>
               <l>And rid from publike office, for bycauſe thou ſtandſt in feare</l>
               <l>A fowle repulſe at peoples hand and ſharpe reproch to beare.</l>
               <l>For go thou not thy Countreys ayde becauſe thou muſt withſtande</l>
               <l>With ſword &amp; ſhield, with tooth &amp; naile thy cruel enmies hand.</l>
               <l>For that is it wherby thy ſtoute and noble minde is tride:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:34"/>
               <l> That is the onely meane to know where thou wilt flée or bide.</l>
               <l>But he whome gréedie goldes deſire or beautie moues awhit,</l>
               <l>Is not to be accompted ſtoute but rather wretched wight.</l>
               <l>For though that filthie coyne to care enforceth miſer men:</l>
               <l>It can not ſo Couragious hearts and noble Natures blen.</l>
               <l>There is no leſſe or baſer thing than is the wretched mynde,</l>
               <l>That is a ſlaue to pelfe, and makes the eye of Reaſon blynde.</l>
               <l>But he Couragious is and ſtoute that richeſſe can deſpiſe,</l>
               <l>Content with poore and meane eſtate, where dread nor trouble lies.</l>
               <l>Or if he haue the worldly wealth, that ſo it packing ſendes,</l>
               <l>As all his ioy conſiſteth in the aiding of his frendes.</l>
               <l>Howe common is the ſaying of King <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> vnto thoſe</l>
               <l>That came from <hi>Rome</hi> to ranſomhome againe his <hi>Romane</hi> foes?</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:34"/>
               <l> Quod Princely <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> to the men that would the money tolde,</l>
               <l>Giue me no great alluring gifts, giue me no glittring gold.</l>
               <l>Let vs with ſword, and not with coyn maintaine the cruell warre:</l>
               <l>For men bright ſhining wepons méet, for Marchants iewels are.</l>
               <l>A worthie worde for ſuch a Prince of ſtoute <hi>Achilles</hi> line,</l>
               <l>It well declard his Noble heart from lucre did decline.</l>
               <l>No leſſe of Courage <hi>Curius</hi> thou werte well knowne to bée</l>
               <l>What time the <hi>Samnites</hi> offred vp their golden gifts to thée:</l>
               <l>For roſting roots thou ſatſt as then by ſlender fiers ſyde,</l>
               <l>When foraine Legates did diſplay their treaſures full of pride.</l>
               <l>More liefer is to me (quod thou) and rather do I wiſhe</l>
               <l>To ſuppe of earthen veſſell, than of ſuch a golden diſhe.</l>
               <l>Wherfore conuey me hence in haſt this golden traſhe againe,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:35"/>
               <l> We will no golde, we rather chooſe in Princelike ſorte to raigne</l>
               <l>Vpon the men that owe the ſame. O words excéeding wiſe,</l>
               <l>Declaring that ſuch vaine delights this Captaine did deſpiſe.</l>
               <l>Beſides with force of bodies might behoueth him to ſtande</l>
               <l>To perill, and the hardeſt things that are, to take in hande</l>
               <l>That will be compted Noble, and of Courage great to bée.</l>
               <l>But yet he muſt in any caſe beware, and wiſely ſée</l>
               <l>He do not raſhly ought attempt but followe Reaſons ſkill,</l>
               <l>And ſhoonne the thing with ſpéedie foote that witte and wiſedome will.</l>
               <l>Let him not venture on the thing that is beyond his might,</l>
               <l>In ſort that he him ſelf therof can neuer well acquite.</l>
               <l>For many times the Bayard bold beyonde his reache wil ronne,</l>
               <l>And beares y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhame for want of power to ende his worke begonne.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:35"/>
               <l> But yet he muſt beware the while in vſing ſuch delay,</l>
               <l>That men coniecture not that he would gladly run his way.</l>
               <l>For better is it farre to dye than lyue with taynt of ſhame,</l>
               <l>Men rather ſhould indure the death than bide the loſſe of fame.</l>
               <l>Encounter not with any man but when of force thou muſt:</l>
               <l>For ſure to blade it, is a thing too beaſtly and vniuſt.</l>
               <l>Warre not vnleſſe it be to haue a quiete peace therby:</l>
               <l>But in thy truce let no deceite or wilie Treaſon lie.</l>
               <l>Nought more agrées to Noble minde than conquerde wights to ſpare:</l>
               <l>In dooyng ſo with Godly kinde he ſéemes to haue a ſhare.</l>
               <l>It earneth not ſo great a prayſe the rebell to ſubdue,</l>
               <l>As doth to be of gentle kinde and Pities traine to ſue.</l>
               <l>The chiefeſt vertue <hi>Caeſar</hi> had that bread his greatſt renowne,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:36"/>
               <l> Was that he vſde no rigour to the captiues of the Towne.</l>
               <l>The Lion ſtoute of curteous kinde hath Nature made to boyes:</l>
               <l>It neuer hurts the yelding pray or humble Beaſt anoyes.</l>
               <l>Fight not with any Foe vnwares, ſtrike not behynde (I ſay)</l>
               <l>For why that kinde of craft is it that cowards doth bewraye.</l>
               <l>Purſue not any man with hate or rancour of thy harte:</l>
               <l>For that of baſe and miſer wights and wretches is the parte.</l>
               <l>If any one vniuſtly ſpeake of thée to thy defame,</l>
               <l>Thinke with thy ſelfe his ſlander doth nowhit deface thy name:</l>
               <l>Saue that his will was fully bent to hurte thée if he might,</l>
               <l>But that his vile and cankred pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe fell not out aright.</l>
               <l>For ſure there is not one aliue that taketh hurt at all</l>
               <l>Of any, leſſe himſelfe be cauſe the miſchiefe do befall.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:36"/>
               <l> For no man once can touch the minde or ſecrete partes within:</l>
               <l>Of any force that can befall thou néedſt not force a pin.</l>
               <l>And when ſo eare thou haſt the power an others harme to frame,</l>
               <l>Let it ſuffiſe thee that thou haſt the powre to do the ſame.</l>
               <l>For no reuenge a greater prayſe dothe purchaſe to a man</l>
               <l>Than for to hold his hands fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wreake when he moſt miſchiefe can.</l>
               <l>Thou ſhalt not with a ſecrete taunt or gyrde another nyp,</l>
               <l>But if thou blame for any thing do it with open lyp.</l>
               <l>A minde not giltie of offence, pure, ſimple, faith vnbroke,</l>
               <l>Are they that make the Noble minde as wittie men haue ſpoke.</l>
               <l>Vnhoneſt dealing, wicked life, and belly full of ſin,</l>
               <l>Ar things that make a fearful wretch, For when the minde within</l>
               <l>Is neuer frée from foule offence, how can a man but quake?</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:37"/>
               <l> The harmeleſſe heart no heauie care can ſadde or ſorie make.</l>
               <l>What néedes he dread y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> liues vpright? death ſhould he feare awhit,</l>
               <l>The gift that Nature hath allowde? by which he commes to ſit</l>
               <l>In bleſſed ſeate with mightie <hi>Ioue?</hi> of torment ſhould he feare,</l>
               <l>Whoſe cruel pangs in his behalfe our God himſelfe doth beare?</l>
               <l>Then wherof ſhould he ſtande in awe, whome <hi>CHRIST</hi> defendeth aye?</l>
               <l>And all the route of heauenly powers aſſiſt as well's they may?</l>
               <l>Who could enforce the Martyrs earſt for tremblyng feare to rue?</l>
               <l>Who coulde by manace or by threates theyr Noble hearts ſubdue?</l>
               <l>Not them could puiſant Princes cauſe or tyrants hands to dred,</l>
               <l>Not armies huge of myghtie force, nor ramping beaſts vnfed.</l>
               <l>Before the Rulers of eſtate youthes, babes, and ſiluer hearde,</l>
               <l>And women, weake by courſe of kind, were neuer once afearde.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:37"/>
               <l> Not bended bow, nor bloodie blades, not brands of fierie flaſhe,</l>
               <l>Nor readie handes with ſtéelie darts, nor fiſtes with fearefull laſhe,</l>
               <l>Not lothſome gayle, nor famine long, not thirſt or other paine,</l>
               <l>Not burning oyle, nor ſcalding pitche, not boyling brine in baine,</l>
               <l>Not golden gifts, not kingly crownes, nor Princes daughters vowde</l>
               <l>In holy bande of mariage theyr conſtant purpoſe bowde.</l>
               <l>And not alone the parents glad their children coulde abide</l>
               <l>To ſée amid the ſcorching fyre, or on the gybet tide:</l>
               <l>But alſo (which is more than that) the louing dame hir ſelfe</l>
               <l>To yelde to torments would perſuade hir weake and wretched Elfe.</l>
               <l>The brother would to brother giue his counſell in the ſame,</l>
               <l>And wife exhorte hir ſpouſe to bide both fier, ſword, and flame.</l>
               <l>Who can report thoſe martyrs were by death yconquerd? No,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:38"/>
               <l> They rather Conquerors (good faith) became by dying ſo.</l>
               <l>There is not any thing aliue more ſtrong or ſturdie than</l>
               <l>The world, the earth, and loftie Skies to yeld to force of man.</l>
               <l>Like bleſſedneſſe vnto a man, or pleaſure can not bée,</l>
               <l>As (mightie God) to quite reſigne the worlde and die to thée:</l>
               <l>And that not by the ſworde alone, or taſting of the death,</l>
               <l>But die to thee by ſcorning of this fleſhe and filthy breath:</l>
               <l>And yet remaine aliue and quick among the wordly wights,</l>
               <l>Not forcing on the fickle ioyes, or fooliſh fonde delights.</l>
               <l>The man that with the ſword is ſlaine is ſure but once to die,</l>
               <l>But who ſo tames his froward fleſhe a thouſand deaths doth trie.</l>
               <l>Nor ery man that doth deſire or couete in his harte</l>
               <l>To die by ſworde, can of the ſworde be ſlaine or haue his part.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:38"/>
               <l> The ſworde is euen a grace of God: and whomſoeuer he</l>
               <l>Voucheſafeth to accept with ſword diſpatched ſo to be,</l>
               <l>That man vndoubtedly in kynde is next to mightie God.</l>
               <l>But now inough my wandring <hi>Muſe</hi> hath rangled farre abrode</l>
               <l>In large diſcourſe of Noble Mindes, nowe time to blowe retreate:</l>
               <l>And with a luckie marching foote the other path to beate.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Temperance.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> Haue of Noble Courage ſayd, both purpoſe place and time</l>
               <l>Of Temperance do will me nowe to write in perfit Rime.</l>
               <l>He temperate may well be termde and calde a modeſt man</l>
               <l>That bridle motions of the mynde with Reaſons ſnaffle can:</l>
               <l>And kéepe <hi>Decorum</hi> in his words, and eke in erye déede.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:39"/>
               <l> Wherefore that ſuch a one thou be (I tell thee) thou haſt néede</l>
               <l>Thy wiſhes well to thinke vpon, and what thou wilt requeſt:</l>
               <l>Purſue the good, and long for that, and let alone the reſt.</l>
               <l>Thoſe things are good that ſimple kind and Nature doe require,</l>
               <l>Not that wherto Ambicious mind and Pride would faine aſpire.</l>
               <l>The man that owes and hath himſelf, not many things doth miſſe:</l>
               <l>He déemes he hath ſuffiſing ſtore that hath hymſelfe ywiſſe.</l>
               <l>He euer flowes &amp; ſwimmes in welſh, and greatly doth abounde:</l>
               <l>We can not ſay he lacketh ought in whome this ſtore is founde.</l>
               <l>For eche himſelfe may by himſelfe and of him ſelfe ſuffiſe,</l>
               <l>If ſo he doe poſſeſſe the good within him ſelfe that lies.</l>
               <l>But he that déemes his owne too ſcant, and ſéekes for foraine ſtuffe,</l>
               <l>A miſers life doth euer leade and neuer hath ynuffe.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:39"/>
               <l> For though his ſtore be neare ſo great yet he in minde doth craue</l>
               <l>A thouſande other things beſide, and greater heape to haue.</l>
               <l>But he (vnleſſe I be deceiu'd himſelfe poſſeſſeth, and</l>
               <l>In good aſſurance of himſelfe ſans other helpe doth ſtande</l>
               <l>That wittie is, and can diſcerne the things that néedefull bée.</l>
               <l>Euen as the man whoſe corps without default of limmes we ſée</l>
               <l>Is compted perfect bodie whole: and eke contrarywiſe</l>
               <l>He taken for a maimed man that lackes one of his eyes,</l>
               <l>Or wants a noſe, a hande, or foote, a legge, or other limme:</l>
               <l>Euen ſo the wight whoſe inward mind and wits are woxen dimme,</l>
               <l>And can not ſée what Reaſon wills for Errours foggie cloude,</l>
               <l>Is compted not to haue himſelfe, nor for a man allowde.</l>
               <l>Wherfore at firſt poſſeſſe thy ſelfe, hunte not for forayn things,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:40"/>
               <l> What can be thine, when that is not that next the bodie clyngs?</l>
               <l>A wittie man hath great deſire diſeaſe away to driue,</l>
               <l>And other hurtfull things to be the longer time aliue.</l>
               <l>Who will of purpoſe poyſon ſucke or taſt of venim vile?</l>
               <l>Who falleth headlong in the dike that may beſtride the ſtile?</l>
               <l>No ſure, if any by miſhap or fraude of other ſup</l>
               <l>Of poyſoned diſhe, to Phiſick ſtreight He bends to belche it vp.</l>
               <l>If by miſfortune any breake his leg, or ioynt it out,</l>
               <l>The Setter of the bone is calde and poaſted for about.</l>
               <l>And thoſe that bleare w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> running eyes haue phiſicke for the ſame:</l>
               <l>And more than that, if ſo by hap thy lumpiſhe Aſſe be lame,</l>
               <l>Thy ſelf on foote for Smith doſt runne a <hi>Vulcan</hi> muſt be had</l>
               <l>To ſhoe the Iade, and heale his héeles his legs are wrapt with wad.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:40"/>
               <l> Then why if any griping griefe thy ſenſe and ſoule poſſeſſe</l>
               <l>Séekſt not with care to cure the ſame and quickly to redreſſe?</l>
               <l>For how much more the Mynd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> corps in Nobleſſe doth excede,</l>
               <l>So much the more regarde the minde than doth the Bodie néede.</l>
               <l>O, to what purpoſe with ſuch toyle and trauaile doſt thou drowne</l>
               <l>Thy corps, &amp; make in doubtful whéele thy Soule to runne ſo rowne?</l>
               <l>Why day and night in feruent heates doſt thou thy body brooſe,</l>
               <l>And doſt meane while thy better parte and chiefeſt member looſe?</l>
               <l>Fie, too vngodly, cruell, and vnto thy ſelfe thou art</l>
               <l>Extreme, that with the propre hands doſt bréede the propre ſmart:</l>
               <l>Why doſt thou maſh thy mind within ſo many nets, from out</l>
               <l>The which thou canſt not rid it, though thou willyng go about?</l>
               <l>Sée how it wakes the day in care and night in noyſome woes,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:41"/>
               <l> And like a thing prickt on with ſpurre vnquiet forth it goes.</l>
               <l>And thou full like a Tormenter with curſt <hi>Bellonas</hi> ſcourge</l>
               <l>The ſielly flying ſoule and hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe minde doſt dayly vrge.</l>
               <l>What? better were it not for thée the loſſe of hande to haue,</l>
               <l>And that wherby thou waxeſt wiſe, in dayntie ſort to ſaue?</l>
               <l>Or than to looſe the part, from heauen that was allotted thée,</l>
               <l>Without the which with other beaſts thou mightſt compared bée?</l>
               <l>How falſe and frayle is all thy hope both liuing here and dead,</l>
               <l>If ſo that member be alacke that ought to be the head?</l>
               <l>Wherfore eſpecially thou muſt the ſickneſſe of the ſoule</l>
               <l>Remoue, that nothing want, and that thou mayſt be perfect whole.</l>
               <l>Direct the ſame by righteſt wayes and plaineſt pathes, that he</l>
               <l>Full well may do his duetie, and the wittie guide may be.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:41"/>
               <l> But (Gentle Reader) to auoide the being ouerlong,</l>
               <l>Accompt that theſe vnto the Soule and perfit Minde belong,</l>
               <l>To hope for that alone which ſtill is ſure to bée a ſtay,</l>
               <l>And ſuch a great ſurpaſſing good as neuer will decay.</l>
               <l>To feare that beyng once befalne for euer and a day</l>
               <l>Will hurt, and ſuch a thing as none relieue with ſuccour may.</l>
               <l>To follow with an earneſt care, and ſtudie all ſuch ioyes</l>
               <l>As no diſcaſe doth daunt awhile or furious face anoyes.</l>
               <l>To ſorow that diſpleaſure whom no pleaſure doth enſue,</l>
               <l>Or by the meanes of whome decayes both life and health to you.</l>
               <l>Force not of other things at all, but of an hoſtage as</l>
               <l>Thou woldſt acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pte fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in haſt the gueſt would gla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly paſſe:</l>
               <l>But rather as a burden deeme and grieuous paine in minde</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:42"/>
               <l> The things to be that ſtoppe thy race, or make thée ſtay behinde</l>
               <l>The Trauailer both car<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ge ſhould and carefull ſickneſſe ſhunne,</l>
               <l>That luckily hee may his courſe and pointed iourney runne.</l>
               <l>And ſure this Life is euen the Path wherin we dayly pace:</l>
               <l>But tother is our Countrey, or of fowle Exile the place.</l>
               <l>If ſo it bee our Countrey, then aſſuredly we ſhall</l>
               <l>To Grandſyers, and our bleſſed frends in peace to ſoiorne all.</l>
               <l>But if Exile and baniſhment to vs it chaunce to bée:</l>
               <l>Then downe we goe to dungeon déepe where is no game nor glée,</l>
               <l>But yelling cries and clamours great, and neuer waſting flame</l>
               <l>Appointed things for due deſert the ſinfull ſoules to tame.</l>
               <l>Thoſe paſſe into their countrey, that by meane of wittie braine</l>
               <l>And Reaſon, ridde themſelues of yll, and did the Good attaine.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:42"/>
               <l> But they contrarywiſe Exile doe ſuffer, that aliue</l>
               <l>In errour dwelt, and in the trade of Vertue coulde not thriue.</l>
               <l>The Minde doth rouing runne aſtray, as often times as it</l>
               <l>Not gouernes, and doth ſée the good, but followes not a whit.</l>
               <l>But nowe we haue digreſt too farre, the cauſe doth will retreate,</l>
               <l>And eke our Methode byds vs of our matter to intreate.</l>
               <l>At firſt of all our meaning was of Motion of the Minde</l>
               <l>That Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perance hight, to tel our tale and of the Modeſt Kinde.</l>
               <l>In this ſhall all my talke conſiſt, this vndertaken charge</l>
               <l>As plainely as we may my <hi>Muſe</hi> and I will ſette at large.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Decorum</hi> chiefly doe obſerue and note with earneſt eye:</l>
               <l>For ſure no ſlender force within his ſéemely boundes doth lie.</l>
               <l>And this <hi>Decorum</hi> double is, that modeſt mindes poſſeſſe,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:43"/>
               <l> One generall and common kinds the other ſomewhat leſſe.</l>
               <l>The common kinde is it that links with Honeſtie in all</l>
               <l>And ech reſpect, and can not from his ſide or footing fall.</l>
               <l>This more apparant is to ſight and to the eares, without</l>
               <l>This generall <hi>Decorum</hi> can be nothing good, no doubt.</l>
               <l>It is naught elſe at all but euen agreement of the things</l>
               <l>Which men do, wel and wiſely worke thence this <hi>Decorum</hi> ſprings,</l>
               <l>And as the forme diſperſed is the bodie quite throughout,</l>
               <l>And is not yet the body but a ſhape ſet on without:</l>
               <l>Euen ſo with Honeſtie and right, <hi>Decorum</hi> doth agrée</l>
               <l>It beautifies the good with ſhape and makes it fayre to ſee.</l>
               <l>And as the Bodies ſeemely ſhewe delightes the lookers eyes,</l>
               <l>And makes them maruell how it could he wrought in goodly wiſe:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:43"/>
               <l> So doth <hi>Decorum</hi> moue the minde, and makes it maruell much</l>
               <l>How that the beautie of the things ſhould happen to bée ſuch.</l>
               <l>Thy ſelfe (good Reader) better mayſt within thy minde deuiſe</l>
               <l>The Nature of the ſame than I in Metre it compriſe.</l>
               <l>The other kinde of decentneſſe is that aſſuredly,</l>
               <l>Which hath his chiefe reſpect vnto that part of Honeſtie</l>
               <l>Which guides the proper motions of the Minde euen as it liſt</l>
               <l>And it in habite, geſture, and in meaſure doth conſiſt</l>
               <l>In voice, and baſhfull bluſhing hue, robes, time, and ſéemely place.</l>
               <l>This makes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou doſt ſtand ſo great within the peoples grace,</l>
               <l>A welcome wight to ery man thys cauſer is of thee,</l>
               <l>That ſuch report and noiſed brute In ery place doth flee.</l>
               <l>Nor do thou ſcorne or ſet at naught what men of thée do déeme:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:44"/>
               <l>'Tis yll the iudgement of the worlde ſo litle to eſtéeme.</l>
               <l>Allow and liſten to theyr doomes, for he is compted prowde</l>
               <l>That doth diſdaine that aught beſides his owne ſhoulde be allowde.</l>
               <l>There are yll fauourde things that do the Mindes of men offende:</l>
               <l>As Arrowes wounde the body when the Archer liſt to bende</l>
               <l>His crooked bow, and ſhoote his ſhafts with nimble hande away.</l>
               <l>And ſuch as do offend, the parts of ſhameleſſe men doe play:</l>
               <l>But thoſe that offer force of hande are too vniuſt we ſay.</l>
               <l>And not alone <hi>Decorum</hi> in the Bodies outwarde ſhow</l>
               <l>Is to be kept and well obſerude, but in the Minde alſo.</l>
               <l>It is an eaſie thing the Minde to frame and faſhion fit,</l>
               <l>As long as Reaſon rules the roſt, and in hir ſeate doth ſit.</l>
               <l>Or (though by happe ſhe be diſplaſte a litle) if ſhe get</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:44"/>
               <l> Hir olde and ſacred roome againe, and raigne deuoide of let.</l>
               <l>Here firſt of all from filthie Ire thou muſt in any wiſe</l>
               <l>Refraine: for it both inwarde minde, and countnance doth diſguiſe.</l>
               <l>What ſight more lothſom ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt thou ſée or looke vpon with eye,</l>
               <l>Than one that is in pelting chafe and angrie moode? for why?</l>
               <l>Full like a Boare he fomes at mouthe whome Curres haue cruell made</l>
               <l>With baulyng barkes on ery ſyde: or like a bedlam Iade</l>
               <l>That wyll not eaſily bide the bitte. Aſſuredly wée can</l>
               <l>The partie that in Anger is not thinke to be a man.</l>
               <l>For then he waxeth out of kinde a ſauage beaſt outright,</l>
               <l>And like a frantike man inragde he lacks his Reaſon quight.</l>
               <l>And after Anger once is calmde, he then repents him ſore</l>
               <l>That he ſo like a ſenſeleſſe man behau'd himſelfe before.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:45"/>
               <l> A meane this miſchief to auoide is at the firſt to caſt</l>
               <l>And wiſely ſcanne within thy breaſt what cauſe of wrath thou haſt.</l>
               <l>Euen as the watchman ſitts a loft to ſpie his cruell foe</l>
               <l>In turrets top, for feare he doe oppreſſe him ere he know:</l>
               <l>So good attendance muſt thou giue leſt anger come vpon,</l>
               <l>And do inuade thée ere thou thinke ſuch fretting malice on:</l>
               <l>And going out of doore as though thou wouldſt to fielde to fight,</l>
               <l>At threſhold claſpe thine armes cloſe in eu'ry point aright.</l>
               <l>And furniſhe ſo thy ſelfe about as though thou ſtoodſt in feare</l>
               <l>Of rouing thieues, that layde to ſpoile the goods in ambuſhe were.</l>
               <l>But if ſo be vnwares thou fall into the well of wrath,</l>
               <l>Sée that thou be not plungde too long within that beaſtly bath:</l>
               <l>And do meanewhile with fretting fiſt no foule offenſe correct:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:45"/>
               <l> For why outragious Anger of the meane hath no reſpect.</l>
               <l>Deteſt exceſſiue crueltie, haue euer that regarde,</l>
               <l>Reuenge for charitie, but do a gentle paine awarde,</l>
               <l>Eſpecially yf father thou thy children puniſh: he</l>
               <l>That is a father ought vnto his children good to be:</l>
               <l>He ſhould not haue a heauie hand, but light, with litle ſmart.</l>
               <l>And where as Kynde within thy breaſt hath grafte a gentle heart,</l>
               <l>Deteſt thy rawe and hungrie rage of fleſhly ſauage ſort,</l>
               <l>That with their teeth to teare the pray doe thinke it paſſing ſport.</l>
               <l>Agayne, you muſt in any caſe auoide and flee away</l>
               <l>From Motion that contrary is to Anger, that in play</l>
               <l>And to much daliance doth delight. For Nature neuer made</l>
               <l>A man to ieſt, but ſhe requires of vs a grauer trade.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:46"/>
               <l> Let all thy wordes to profite more than to a pleaſure tende,</l>
               <l>Deale moſt in earneſt, but in ieſt thy winde but ſeldome ſpende.</l>
               <l>Yet Nature doth not quite denie a man to ſport and ieſt:</l>
               <l>But yet to holde the golden meane ſhe thinkes it euer beſt.</l>
               <l>It is not ſéemely too too grim or ouer harde to bée,</l>
               <l>And reape but hate for ſolemne lookes: nor yet for to much glée</l>
               <l>To be deſpiſde and had in ſcorne. By Ieſting do not craue</l>
               <l>Vaingloriouſly throughout the Town a Ieſters name to haue.</l>
               <l>As we allowe the wearie man a tyme of quiet reſt,</l>
               <l>To eaſe his penſiue pained limmes with labours long oppreſt:</l>
               <l>Euen ſo with ſeldome prettie ieſtes thou mayſt refreſhe thy wit,</l>
               <l>But then thou muſt ſo place thy words and ſayings, as may fit</l>
               <l>And beſt agrée with grauitie. Sée that thy ieſt be ſuche</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:46"/>
               <l> As may both honeſt be eſtéemde, and ery way may touche</l>
               <l>Both honeſt ſhame, and good deuiſe, and Witte in ery caſe.</l>
               <l>Beſides when time requires thou ſhalt not raſhely runne thy race</l>
               <l>As bedlam Roges do vſe to do, or like a poſting ſlaue.</l>
               <l>Let all thy Ieſtes be weightie, and thy ieſture very graue.</l>
               <l>Let not thy voice be ouerlowde, goe not to faſt aboute,</l>
               <l>For feare thy haſtie pace offend and trouble all the route.</l>
               <l>Beware in any wiſe thy wordes no Anger doe prouoke</l>
               <l>Or heauie chéere to any man: let nought that thou haſt ſpoke</l>
               <l>With bitter girding breede offence. With rankling tooth to neare</l>
               <l>Let not thy babling bite or touch the man that doth it heare.</l>
               <l>Ne doth my writing Laughter barre, ſo that in modeſt meane</l>
               <l>You vſe the ſame: for otherwiſe it ſpills the countnance cleane.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:47"/>
               <l> For too muche laughing marres y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> looke for boyes is laughter fitte,</l>
               <l>And gigling dames that Reaſon want and haue but ſlender witte.</l>
               <l>Who ſo at theft doth girne and laugh and thereof makes a game,</l>
               <l>Or ſmiles to ſée an others harme, is very much to blame.</l>
               <l>In Playes auoyde the filthie gaine: for certainly by play</l>
               <l>Is nothing got but waſting yll the golden time away.</l>
               <l>If yong thou be in luſtie age and haſt thy limmes in prime:</l>
               <l>Some painfull practiſe doe deuiſe to paſſe away the time,</l>
               <l>An exerciſe to trie thy force: but with diſcretion vſe</l>
               <l>The ſame, and do beware thou do no limme or member bruſe.</l>
               <l>I ſundry times haue ſéene an olde man play and vſe diſport,</l>
               <l>But yet (good faith) it hath bene all in good and ſober ſort.</l>
               <l>But neuer ſaw I in my life a youth delight in game,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:47"/>
               <l> Of whom I could conceyue that hée to good would euer frame.</l>
               <l>When thou with ſtudie wearie art, and that thou haſt a will</l>
               <l>To ſolace, cope with learned heads, and men of tried ſkyll.</l>
               <l>For conference both holeſome is, and eke increaſeth wit.</l>
               <l>Do bridle bothe thy mouth, and <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> parte with pinching bit,</l>
               <l>At randon neuer let them runne: for he that loues to féede</l>
               <l>Too muche, and <hi>Venus</hi> mynion is, he is a beaſt in déede,</l>
               <l>And onely but a Man in name, for ſhape accompted ſo,</l>
               <l>Bicauſe he doth from place to place in manly perſon go.</l>
               <l>What? ery man may ſoone ſuppreſſe <hi>Cupidoes</hi> flames, if he</l>
               <l>Withdraw ſuch things as to the fire in ſtéede of faggots be:</l>
               <l>Or if he neuer beate his braines, and fire his fonde deſire</l>
               <l>On things that are by Nature apt to ſtirre that ſcorching fire,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:48"/>
               <l> Not taking in too many cuppes: if thou be wiſe take héede</l>
               <l>Howe to the doubtfull ſkirmiſh thou with <hi>Venus</hi> doſt procéede,</l>
               <l>Or fight to much with bellie fare. Liſt not at all to trie</l>
               <l>How honeſt and howe ſober thou couldſt by a <hi>Thais</hi> lie.</l>
               <l>When Wine and Women are at ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d truſt not thy force to much:</l>
               <l>For fire will quickly take the towe if it the towe doe touche.</l>
               <l>When ſo thou liſt to conquere ſinne and beaſtly liuing, fight</l>
               <l>Not neare at hande, but haue thy foe a greate wayes off in ſight.</l>
               <l>Let wanton mates not enter in thy houſe in any wiſe,</l>
               <l>Doe barre thy doore with biggeſt bolt: for ſure no ſafetie lyes</l>
               <l>In coping with ſuch hatefull gueſts, they neuer will away</l>
               <l>Without the conqueſt till they doe thy fotted carcas ſlaye.</l>
               <l>No triumph in this doubtfull caſe is to be had or woon,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:48"/>
               <l> Vnleſſe we ſhewe the foe our héeles and from the battaile roon.</l>
               <l>And ſure (a maruells thing to tell) the Palme alone is due</l>
               <l>To him, and he is Victor that in poaſt from fighting flue.</l>
               <l>But if ſo thou by Fortune chaunce <hi>Cupidos</hi> thrall to bée,</l>
               <l>Redéeme thy ſelfe in all the haſt: thou néedſt a ſlender fée</l>
               <l>Or ſumme to raunſome home againe thy ſelfe if thou be wyſe,</l>
               <l>Shake fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy neck that ſeruage yoke that on thy ſhoulders lies.</l>
               <l>Vſe force, and flée: for ſtay is full of daunger out of dout,</l>
               <l>The longer ſtay, the worſer ſtate. And who ſo goes about</l>
               <l>To flatter Madame <hi>Venus,</hi> he ſhall ſuffer greater ſmart,</l>
               <l>And feele the flame the hotter farre that fretts the Louers hart.</l>
               <l>And ſince thou art a man by kynde of ſect and ſéede diuine,</l>
               <l>As God is farre from fleſhe, ſo thou from fleſhe muſt farre decline.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:49"/>
               <l>Though thou in ſecrete do offence and no man ſée thy face,</l>
               <l>Yet thou as witneſſe euer gainſt thy ſelfe doſt ſtande in place.</l>
               <l>Why doſt thou more than of thy ſelfe an others preſence feare?</l>
               <l>Since thou a witneſſe in thy breaſt againſt thy ſelfe doſt beare.</l>
               <l>It litle ſkills where any ſee thy doings yea or no:</l>
               <l>For day and night thy Conſcience of erye thing doth knowe</l>
               <l>In all eſtates the luſt of fleſhe a foule offence is thought,</l>
               <l>But more vnſéemely in an olde and Aged man is nought.</l>
               <l>For why? the white and ſiluer heares the witleſſe youth ſhould guide</l>
               <l>By Counſell and by good aduiſe for feare they wander wide.</l>
               <l>And therfore ought they al theyr talke to frame ſo wiſe and graue,</l>
               <l>In preſence of the youth, as they of them may honour haue.</l>
               <l>For this in former paſſed times was Age in honour had,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:49"/>
               <l>For this alone the Fathers were accompted graue and ſad.</l>
               <l>But on the other ſide againe let youth do reuerence</l>
               <l>To aged Syres, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y to them be ſuccour and defence.</l>
               <l>When ancient Syres to Court do go, or on the holy day</l>
               <l>To church, a rout of youth ſhould then awaite them on the way.</l>
               <l>And make their choyce among them al whome ech doth fanſie beſt,</l>
               <l>And whom he could content himſelfe withall aboue the reſt.</l>
               <l>For ſure it is a perfite ſigne of Vertue in a man,</l>
               <l>To reuerence an aged wight in humbleſt wiſe he can.</l>
               <l>Let youth with pacience fall to paines to make their bodies harde:</l>
               <l>From Wine &amp; Women but they muſt in any caſe be barde.</l>
               <l>Let groſſe and homely be theyr fare no dainties in their diſhe,</l>
               <l>The belly muſt be fillde, but not as much as throate coulde wiſhe.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:50"/>
               <l> Let neuer yong men haunt the Cooks where curious Cates be meſt,</l>
               <l>Let that ſuffiſe them that at home in Fathers houſe is dreſt.</l>
               <l>No, neither when they come to age and youth is gone and paſt,</l>
               <l>Let them be ydle and vnwrought, or filthie pleaſure taſte.</l>
               <l>For who denies but aged men may many things diſpatch?</l>
               <l>Let them or write with pen, or at their ſtudies haue a ſnatche</l>
               <l>As ſoone as they returne from Church, when ſeruice time is paſt:</l>
               <l>That exerciſe is good as long as morning Sunne doth laſt.</l>
               <l>But let the Boy be then at Booke and leſſon learne by hart,</l>
               <l>'Tis eaſie to inforce a childe from ſtudie not to ſtart:</l>
               <l>He eaſily will beare the yoke. but do not force awhit</l>
               <l>Although he can not worde by worde his leſſon well recite.</l>
               <l>For ſéede that in the ſoile is ſowne lies hidden long below,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:50"/>
               <l> And many monthes is vnder grounde, but yet at laſt doth grow:</l>
               <l>And all the while in bellie of his mother Earth it lies,</l>
               <l>The want of humour in the ſéede. the moiſtie ſoile ſupplies.</l>
               <l>Likewiſe what ſo the childe doth lerne and takes in tender yeares,</l>
               <l>In after time when age comes on the frute it ſelfe appeares.</l>
               <l>Let graue and decent be thy wéede, be modeſt in aray:</l>
               <l>For feare thy outwarde garment doe thine inwarde kinde bewray.</l>
               <l>For ſundry nice vnmanly men by nice attire are ſpid,</l>
               <l>And by that meanes breakes out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bile that was in couert hid.</l>
               <l>The filthie whelke and bladder redde appearing on the ſkin,</l>
               <l>Declares vnto the lookers on the blood corrupt within.</l>
               <l>Thinke that ſuch niceneſſe appertains vnto the womans kind:</l>
               <l>And yet I can not praiſe the wench in whome that vice I finde.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:51"/>
               <l> Extreme or ouer great to be. wherefore if ſo thou haue</l>
               <l>That fault, imbrace it not to much, nor doe thou euer craue</l>
               <l>To haue it if thou once be frée and quit from ſuch a vice:</l>
               <l>For ſure it is a filthie thing a man to be too nice.</l>
               <l>Both womans wede and wanton gate refuſe in any caſe,</l>
               <l>And thinke that they are euer apt mans Nature to deface.</l>
               <l>Fye, ſhame vpon it, what is more againſt our manly kinde,</l>
               <l>Than vnderneath a womans wéede the ſhape of man to finde?</l>
               <l>Yet let thy garments handſom bée not ſluttiſh, leſt the Fame</l>
               <l>And common rumour yelde to thée a fowle and filthie name.</l>
               <l>Kéepe thou amid the two extremes: ne, though thou haue no ſtore</l>
               <l>Or great exceſſe of welth, thou muſt a ſlouen be the more.</l>
               <l>For neither muſt the poore man goe too ſluttiſh in his wéede.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:51"/>
               <l> Nor doth the man that barrs thée from this niceneſſe here in déede,</l>
               <l>Perſuade thée to be ouer rude, or to vncleane aray:</l>
               <l>But highly doth with all his heart commende the middle way.</l>
               <l>What ſo comes nere y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> two extremes vnſéemely is and yll:</l>
               <l>The Middle is the Vertues place, there ſhe is planted ſtill.</l>
               <l>Let ſimple cheere content thy minde not bankets coſtly dight:</l>
               <l>Such chéere as well from famine may thy emptie belly quight.</l>
               <l>Sufficing let thy table bée, let pleaſure not redounde</l>
               <l>Therin to much, but euer there let meate inough be founde.</l>
               <l>Let hunger be in ſteade of ſauſe and ſtirre the ſtomacke vp,</l>
               <l>Delight thou not of ſyrops ſwéete deuiſde by arte to ſuppe.</l>
               <l>Force not thy chaunge of diſhes, but for holeſome victuals ſéeke,</l>
               <l>And reſt content with cates that erſt thy Fathers olde did léeke.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:52"/>
               <l> Nor do accompt ſo greatly of the Kitchen glorie, but</l>
               <l>Thy whole delight and ſtudie in a ſober dyet put.</l>
               <l>Ne ſhalt thou be ſo ſparefull as a Niggards name to get,</l>
               <l>And cauſe that ery man on thée his hatefull téeth ſhall whet.</l>
               <l>Be not ſeuere in ſlender things, nor ſéeke to ſet no lawes</l>
               <l>In ſort to banniſhe mirth, and bée of drouſie dumpes the cauſe.</l>
               <l>For trifling toyes full many times a great rebuke do bring:</l>
               <l>And yet from thence doth ſlender gain and litle profite ſpring.</l>
               <l>And where <hi>Decorum</hi> many parts and cauſes hath, the beſt</l>
               <l>And chiefe conſiſtes in that we know <hi>Decoru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> how to wreſt.</l>
               <l>For not in ery time is one ſelfe thing allowde for good:</l>
               <l>As <hi>Proteus</hi> Monſter ſundry ſhapes did ſhift in one ſelfe hood.</l>
               <l>Looke what became and fitted youth in gréene and tender yeares,</l>
               <l>For aged Syres vnſéemely ſhewes,
<pb facs="tcp:21003:52"/> full ſoone the oddes appeares.</l>
               <l>State, Office, time, and preſent age a difference great doe make,</l>
               <l>And cauſeth thee what earſt became vnſeemely now to take.</l>
               <l>And what a priuate man before thou likedſt well, as nowe</l>
               <l>To Office calld in common weale thou muſt not once allowe.</l>
               <l>The furious phraſe thou vſde in field encountring with thy Foe,</l>
               <l>Behoues thée nowe a quiet man in Citie to forgoe.</l>
               <l>If bending thou to aged yeares in practiſe doe delight</l>
               <l>That fitted youth, aſſure thy ſelfe thou ſwaruſt from Duetie quight.</l>
               <l>And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou art wel ſtept in age if then thy maners bee</l>
               <l>Not altred, but w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> youthful pranks and pageants doe agrée,</l>
               <l>Then doſt thou wax a Mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſter ſowle whome men of right ſhould flée.</l>
               <l>In youth thou wiſhte to come to age and ſiluer heares to haue:</l>
               <l>So now thou ſhouldſt another life and other hoſtage craue.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:53"/>
               <l> Well may we laugh the Sot to ſcorne that in his latter dayes,</l>
               <l>Much like a babe in cradle clowtes doth fall to childiſh playes.</l>
               <l>Loke how thy prieſtly garments do from others diſagrée,</l>
               <l>So much differring ought thy life from other mens to bée.</l>
               <l>And how much higher is thy roome and office, ſo much more</l>
               <l>Thou oughtſt thy maners to regarde than thou wert wont before.</l>
               <l>Doe not as common ſort of men, ſince fewe or none at all</l>
               <l>May match with thée: to higher things and déeper matters fall.</l>
               <l>If thou in place appointed be of Lyon ſtoute to ſitte,</l>
               <l>Then be a Mouſe no more, but doe as is for Lions fittte.</l>
               <l>And ſithens <hi>CHRIST</hi> hath thée endude with Eagles gleaming eyes,</l>
               <l>Dyg not the groo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d as Ants are wont, but viewe the loftie ſkies.</l>
               <l>When earſt a ſouldiers life thou ladſt thou threwſt thy darts apace,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:53"/>
               <l> Now being Souldier vnto Chriſt in ſtede of darte and mace</l>
               <l>Take vp his Croſſe, &amp; fight therwith. When Phiſicke was thy Art</l>
               <l>Thou dydſt by Phiſicke baniſh griefe from ery lymme and parte:</l>
               <l>But nowe a Shephierd waxen thou thy ſiellie flocke ſhouldſt féede.</l>
               <l>The Shephierd watching all the night of folde doth take his héede</l>
               <l>For feare the fowle &amp; fretting Woult with harſhe and hungry iawe</l>
               <l>Do cruſhe his Cattell, and conuey the fleſhe into his mawe.</l>
               <l>No, neither is it thought inough a man himſelfe to ſaue,</l>
               <l>But that he muſt as great regarde vnto his cattell haue.</l>
               <l>And he that with his proper life can take it well in grée</l>
               <l>To loaſe his flocke, deſerues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> folde and roome remoude to bée.</l>
               <l>A number chale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge Shephierds names and woulde be coumpted ſo,</l>
               <l>But falſly they vſurpe the ſame as do their dealings ſhow.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:54"/>
               <l> For neither haue they any carke of weake and hungrie flocks:</l>
               <l>Nor though thei had, thei could do more than ſtones or woodden ſtocks</l>
               <l>As touching pointes for Paſtors fit. 'tis ſeldome where to ſée</l>
               <l>A Shephierd well content with that he hath: although he bée</l>
               <l>As full and throughly ſtuft as may his ſwollen belly holde:</l>
               <l>Yet long his gaping guts to féele a farther taſt of golde.</l>
               <l>Beſides to keepe <hi>Decorum</hi> full and eary way to hit,</l>
               <l>Thou muſt reſpect vnto thy kinde what Perſon beſt will fit.</l>
               <l>For where as him it well becomes to ſet his Countnaunce ſad,</l>
               <l>It beſt beſéemes an other man to looke with viſage glad.</l>
               <l>And if that one will counterfaict a ſadde and ſolemne grace</l>
               <l>And looke demure, a man ſhall ſhape a Woodcock by his face.</l>
               <l>And if that other fall to mirth and vſe a gameſome glée,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:54"/>
               <l> It fits but yll vnto his kinde, it will vndecent bée.</l>
               <l>One gentle is and curteous wight, his talke is ioynde with ieſt:</l>
               <l>An other can not frame with dumpes a paſſing pleaſant gueſt.</l>
               <l>This man is ſimple, full of truth, and loues to ſtande with right:</l>
               <l>An other hath in curious talke and filed phraſe delight.</l>
               <l>Wherfore let eche man follow that wherto his kinde agrées,</l>
               <l>Eſpecially in that wherin no Vice at all he ſées.</l>
               <l>To marke the wittie Huſbandman I thinke it not amis,</l>
               <l>That grafts his grifts in ery ſoyle as fitte and gréeing is.</l>
               <l>For firſt he notes the perfect Kind and Nature of the grounde,</l>
               <l>And wher he thinks y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts wil proue with plants he ſetts it rounde.</l>
               <l>In hilles aloft the Vine is plaſt, in vale the Alder trée:</l>
               <l>The Oliue in a drier vaine, for that dothe beſt agrée.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:55"/>
               <l> Where colde and chillie is the ground the Cheſtnut he is pight:</l>
               <l>The fat and blacker earth is it where Apple trées delight.</l>
               <l>The grauell and the Sandy ſoile the Franckincenſe doth loue,</l>
               <l>And in the harde and ſtonie plot the Citron Pome doth proue.</l>
               <l>With mount the Peare can beſt away in Moore the Willow growes:</l>
               <l>The Plane trée waxeth ſooneſt big where Water freſhly flowes.</l>
               <l>Wherfore reſpect thy proper Kinde and to thy Nature cleaue,</l>
               <l>For ery mans becomes him beſt, all others natures leaue.</l>
               <l>Indeuour by thine owne deuiſe and wiſe forecaſting braine</l>
               <l>To purchaſe Glorie, others gifts contende not to attaine.</l>
               <l>For looke what ſtarres allotted haue can no man well auoyde:</l>
               <l>Nor, what the Planets doe denie, can euer be enioyde. <note place="margin">Eche thing followes his propre kind.</note>
               </l>
               <l>When will the fearfull waking Hart do way his quiuering dread?</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:55"/>
               <l> When will the Bull the Lion match for all his horned head?</l>
               <l>When wil the Lamb not fear y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Wolf? or take him for his foe?</l>
               <l>When will the ſharp &amp; prickeard Foxe his kindly fraude forgoe?</l>
               <l>When wil the Hare not dread y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Dog? or ſtande of Houndes in awe?</l>
               <l>When wil the Moorecock leaue to diue with Fiſhe to fill his mawe?</l>
               <l>The coleblacke Crow ſhall neuer ſing ſo ſwéetely as the Swan,</l>
               <l>Although he crie with cleareſt pipes and pleaſantſt note he can.</l>
               <l>The Goate will not forgo the woods but treade the yuie trée,</l>
               <l>The ſlender legged Frog will ſtill in plaſhe and puddles be.</l>
               <l>The wofull Turtle neuer will from dolefull dities blyn,</l>
               <l>But aye bewaile his louing Make when he doth once begyn.</l>
               <l>A man that ſayes againſt the haire to practiſe any thing</l>
               <l>Is like to him that would his ſhip gainſt Tide and water bring.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:56"/>
               <l> And certes who ſoeuer thinkes agaynſt the ſtreame to ſayle</l>
               <l>May ſtande aſſurde his fonde attempt can neuer long preuaile.</l>
               <l>For when his fainting elbowes yelde and armes giue vp, the Tide</l>
               <l>Doth beate him backe as faſt againe vpon the other ſide.</l>
               <l>So often he that cares not for his owne, but couets moſt</l>
               <l>For other mens, gains neither theirs and yet his owne hath loſt.</l>
               <l>And ſundry times the Gnuffe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gripes a thing full faſt in fiſt</l>
               <l>For gréedineſſe of nouell praie, both this and that hath miſt.</l>
               <l>If <hi>Praetor</hi> thée or <hi>Tribune</hi> will to take vpon thy backe an Office, in the which thou doſt both ſkill and practiſe lacke,</l>
               <l>As thus perhaps, to tell a tale and preach in open preſſe</l>
               <l>Where thou but litle Grammer haſt and Rhetoricke much leſſe:</l>
               <l>Then well conſider thou before, ſéeke learned mens aduiſe,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:56"/>
               <l> Learne that wherof thou haſt no ſkil, let labour helpe the diſe.</l>
               <l>So that although thou canſt not win renoume or Noble fame:</l>
               <l>Yet that thou mayſt auoide reproche and ſcape from ſlanders ſhame.</l>
               <l>What kinde of life thou vndertakſte purſue and follow ſtill:</l>
               <l>Vnleſſe thou haue good Reaſon why thou ſhouldſt exchaunge thy will.</l>
               <l>And do it ſo as other men may ſée the Reaſon why</l>
               <l>Thou from thy olde and former trade on ſodayn ſo doſt fly.</l>
               <l>Be not vncertaine like the winde, but as occaſion lies</l>
               <l>Chaunge thou thy purpoſe and intent: be ſayd in any wiſe</l>
               <l>And conſtant, but beware thou be not marride to thy minde</l>
               <l>And ouerthwart, as many are of vile and rebell kinde.</l>
               <l>For doubtleſſe (this I know for ſooth) is moſt aſſurde and true,</l>
               <l>'Tis compted lightneſſe for a man to chaunge his trade anew.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:57"/>
               <l> But if ſo it be raſhly done, then ſhame enſues the déede:</l>
               <l>And when thou mindſt to chop, beware of ouerhaſtie ſpéede.</l>
               <l>For ſodaine chaunge doth euer make men wonder very ſore,</l>
               <l>Suſpecting what the cauſe ſhould be of chaunging euermore.</l>
               <l>When thou art callde to Office, ſhift away thy priuate minde:</l>
               <l>And thinke that thou to be the head of many art aſſignde.</l>
               <l>For then by thée the people ſpeakes, thy tongue and theirs is one:</l>
               <l>By thée the people heares and ſées, thou art their ſtay alone.</l>
               <l>Wherfore good reaſon is it that their profite thou prouide,</l>
               <l>To whom the publike Office hath appointed thée a guide.</l>
               <l>The Common profite euer ought to be preferde of right</l>
               <l>Before a priuate members gaine. The Officer ſhould quight:</l>
               <l>Forget and be vnmindefull of him ſelfe in any caſe,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:57"/>
               <l> The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue regard what beſt beſemes a man in ſuch a place</l>
               <l>Poſſeſſing ſeate of awfull rule, change wéede and woonted face:</l>
               <l>I meane behauiour vſed earſt before thou borſte a ſway.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Praetor</hi> many things forbids, and ſo the <hi>Conſul</hi> may</l>
               <l>Which priuate men can not controll. beſides the Place and Time</l>
               <l>Allowe not ſundry things for good which are withouten crime</l>
               <l>And good at any other ſtemme. <hi>Pericles</hi> chafed ſore</l>
               <l>With <hi>Sophocles</hi> that was his mate and ſelfe ſame office bore,</l>
               <l>And worthily rebuked him bicauſe he did beholde</l>
               <l>A pretie boy, when he of lawes his tale and ſentence tolde.</l>
               <l>But if ſo be his fellowe had in fielde or wreſtling place</l>
               <l>Done ſo, <hi>Pericles</hi> to haue chyd would neuer had the face.</l>
               <l>Wherfore as in a Lute the ſtrings and fretts do all agrée:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:58"/>
               <l> To pleaſe the longing eares of them that liſten to the glée:</l>
               <l>So Perſon, Tyme, the Place, the Age and ery thing beſide</l>
               <l>Muſt all accorde, and as it were bée all in one allide</l>
               <l>In him that publike perſon beares. The Priuate man likewiſe</l>
               <l>Muſt practiſe Iuſtice with his féeres, not ſtudie how to riſe</l>
               <l>Or ſéeke to preſſe his equalls downe, and vnder foote to treade.</l>
               <l>Yet would I not a Citizen perſuade to put his head</l>
               <l>Beneth his girdle that is not his better in eſtate,</l>
               <l>And whom the Common lawes allow his fellow and his mate.</l>
               <l>Be not ſo ſimple ſotted as to beare away the ſcoffe</l>
               <l>Or be deſpiſde of any man, or naught accompted off.</l>
               <l>And whilſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> woldſt be gentle thought and of a curteous kinde,</l>
               <l>Take héede thou be not ouermylde. let none haue powre to fynde</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:58"/>
               <l> Ambition lodging in thy breſt or boldneſſe ouermuch:</l>
               <l>Submit thy ſelfe, but not to low, be egall vnto ſuch</l>
               <l>As are thy péeres: ne yet deſpiſe inferiours vnto thée,</l>
               <l>And with good will do honour thoſe thy betters farre that bée.</l>
               <l>Yet ſtande not too too much (I ſay) of higher Powres in awe:</l>
               <l>For he that leades his life vpright hath néede to feare no lawe.</l>
               <l>O God, howe great deſire ſhould dwel within thy heart of right</l>
               <l>To haue a conſcience clere from ſinne that feare abandons quight.</l>
               <l>Be not ſeditious, but with all thy powre do practiſe peace,</l>
               <l>For that is it which cauſer is that Publike weales increaſe.</l>
               <l>Do honour due and reuerence to ſuch Eſtates as bare</l>
               <l>The office earſt, and ſuch as now do wield the Common care:</l>
               <l>Yea eu'ry ſuch as bruted is to be of Vertues bande.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:59"/>
               <l> It is a goodly matter for the childe in awe to ſtande</l>
               <l>And reuerence of his auncient Syres, and ſuch as parentes are.</l>
               <l>If thou by fortune trauaile from thy natiue countrey far,</l>
               <l>And make abode in foraine Towne, deale not in any caſe</l>
               <l>Or medle once with any rules or cuſtomes of the place,</l>
               <l>But to thy priuate buſineſſe haue thou reſpect for aye,</l>
               <l>Leaſt any (ſtranger pack thou hence) by happe to thée doe ſaye.</l>
               <l>Nor if thou be a Townſman and within the Citie borne,</l>
               <l>Thou ſhalt no Pilgrim ſéeme to hate or of a ſtraunger ſcorne,</l>
               <l>But yelde good entertainment vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all that come and goe:</l>
               <l>Be friende to all that trauaile, and not once to one a foe.</l>
               <l>For he that cuts the Strangers throte or curriſh is to thoſe</l>
               <l>That trauaile Countreys, leaues to be a man, and headlong goes</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:59"/>
               <l> Into the boundes of beaſtly kinde. For why <hi>Lycaon</hi> was</l>
               <l>A Woulfe eſtéemde, bicauſe that be for crueltie did paſſe,</l>
               <l>To forainers that chaunſt to come where he his hoſtage helde.</l>
               <l>Thinke ery burden to be borne that thou mayſt fitly weld:</l>
               <l>But all vnhoneſt filthy things may not be borne withall.</l>
               <l>For ſure a fowle vnciuile thing the bearers necke doth gall</l>
               <l>As yoke doth pinch the heyfers throte. Eſchue the thing that gaines</l>
               <l>An yll report, and the with fréekes of filthie rumor ſtaines.</l>
               <l>Thy ſhamefull partes of Nature thou ſhalt couertly conceale:</l>
               <l>For Kinde hir ſelfe doth will thée ſo in honeſt wiſe to deale.</l>
               <l>When ſo a Player comes on ſtage he ties his trinkets harde,</l>
               <l>For feare if ought ſhould fal, the plays <hi>Decorum</hi> ſhould be marde.</l>
               <l>Then ſuffer not for very ſhame a ſcaffold vice that may</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:60"/>
               <l> Vnciuile be by reaſon of his licence in the play,</l>
               <l>In Ciuile nurture thée to paſſe. beleue not ſuch as déenie</l>
               <l>That eary word that they do ſpeake doth paſſing well beſéeme,</l>
               <l>But do eſchue in any wiſe and filthie language flée:</l>
               <l>Eſpecially in open place when men giue eare to thée.</l>
               <l>For ſhamefull talke doth wel declare the ſpeaker of the ſame</l>
               <l>To be a man from Reaſon farre, and quight abhorring ſhame.</l>
               <l>But if by hap of force thou muſt and matter ſo require,</l>
               <l>To tell thy tale in clenlieſt wiſe by circumſtance deſire.</l>
               <l>For lothſome language pierceth déepe into the inwarde part,</l>
               <l>And doth torment the quiet minde and well diſpoſed hart.</l>
               <l>Deteſt it as thou wouldſt a thing that Carrionlike did ſmell:</l>
               <l>Or as an Iſie place where none can faſten footing well.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:60"/>
               <l> For filthy ſauours noy the noſe, the ſlipper Path the féete:</l>
               <l>But beaſtly ſpeach the maners marrs that elſe would ſéeme diſcréete.</l>
               <l>Let none preſume in things wherof he hath no perfect grounde</l>
               <l>To chat, for preſent may be ſome that will his words confounde.</l>
               <l>Let him that little Latine can in Gréeke not wade to farre,</l>
               <l>Nor him that ſmatters Greke tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlate olde <hi>Maro,</hi> leſt he marre</l>
               <l>The grace and beautie of his verſe: Let him that ſtudies lawe</l>
               <l>Not meddle wyth the Phyſicke Arte for feare he ſéeme to rawe.</l>
               <l>Beſides a handſome ieſture muſt obſerued bée in gate.</l>
               <l>For ery man beholdes him well that goes abrode: the ſtate</l>
               <l>Of all our maners many times is déemed by the ſame,</l>
               <l>And men that want <hi>Decorum</hi> there do beare away the blame.</l>
               <l>The going ſhewes the mindes conceit. Let not thy gate be ſlowe,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:61"/>
               <l> Nor do not with too quicke a foote or pace too haſtie goe:</l>
               <l>But vſe the meane amid them both. It likes me not at all</l>
               <l>Thou ſtalk like him that bears a meſſe of gruell to the hall:</l>
               <l>Or like the maide in ſolemne ſort that to the temple wendes</l>
               <l>At dauncing day, when ſhe to chooſe a fellow mate intendes.</l>
               <l>But yet I woulde not haue thée vſe ſuch poſting haſt as might</l>
               <l>Both make thée pant &amp; want thy wind, or fall downe hedlong right.</l>
               <l>And eke thou ſhalt as great a part of good <hi>Decorum</hi> ſée</l>
               <l>In talke and language, and as much for that commended be.</l>
               <l>When ſo among thy fellowes thou thy tale doſt happe to tell,</l>
               <l>Let not thy voyce be ouerlowde, for that agrées not well.</l>
               <l>But in aſſemble to pronounce when ſo thou haſt a cauſe,</l>
               <l>To th'end thy tale may perce their ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res do ſtretch awide thy iawes.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:61"/>
               <l> Yet vtter plainely all thy words with voice both lowde and ſhrill,</l>
               <l>For Nature and thy helping hand that purpoſe further will.</l>
               <l>If ſo thy matters be of weight, ſeuerely ſet thy grace:</l>
               <l>If light and of importance ſmall, vſe ſwéete and ſmiling face.</l>
               <l>In iudgement ſharper than in talke looke that thou euer bée:</l>
               <l>Let life be more ſeuere than lookes, doe learne this rule of me.</l>
               <l>Do ſauſe thy talke with pretie ieſt, and yelde with willing minde</l>
               <l>Vnto thy fellow, looke a prayſe for doing ſo to finde.</l>
               <l>Sée that thou euer blaſe a trouth, but not to ſcolding fall</l>
               <l>With any man, of force thou muſt obſerue a meane withall.</l>
               <l>For ſure ſufficeth thée to ſay thy minde is nothing ſo:</l>
               <l>Vſe no contentious talke with hym in any caſe, altho</l>
               <l>He doe defende the other part. Vnto thy fellowes harke</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:62"/>
               <l> Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou haſt ſayd, 'tis ſhame for thée alone to bawle and barke.</l>
               <l>If any ſtande in ſtubborne ſort maintaining nought at all</l>
               <l>But falſhode, yeld, for feare your talke to greater miſchief fall.</l>
               <l>Although the tale which any man in preſence mindes to tell</l>
               <l>No whit delight thy curious eares or fanſie paſſing well:</l>
               <l>Yet trouble not the reſt that would giue eare vnto the talke,</l>
               <l>But rather paciently endure all others tongs to walke,</l>
               <l>And doe but ſeldome ſpeake thy ſelfe. If thou be ſad by kinde</l>
               <l>Reproue nor fynde no fault with thoſe that are of mery minde.</l>
               <l>Deſpiſe thou none for that thy ſelfe in wiſedome doſt excéede.</l>
               <l>But rather ayde them if thou mayſt by good aduiſe at néede.</l>
               <l>In ſpeaking euer doe beware and wiſely looke about,</l>
               <l>For feare the ſickneſſe of the minde by babbling burſt not out.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:62"/>
               <l> Nip no man in his abſence, for (no doubt) 'tis traitorlike,</l>
               <l>A man that is not ware of thée behinde his backe to ſtrike.</l>
               <l>But rather looke wher whilſt thou doſt an other ſharply touch,</l>
               <l>Thou doe not by the ſelfe ſame meane controll thy ſelfe as much.</l>
               <l>What ſo they are thou ſpeakſt vnto do curteouſly entreate:</l>
               <l>The leſſer ſort thou ſhalt not ſcorne no more than of the great.</l>
               <l>But rather trauaile and thou canſt to beare a ſhewe and face</l>
               <l>As though thou madſt accompt of all: this prouerbe taketh place,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Who ſo doth lone, is loude againe.</hi> by curteous language we</l>
               <l>Muſt chiefly couet in good will of ery man to bée.</l>
               <l>But moſt of all our frendſhip olde muſt be reſpected ſtill:</l>
               <l>And greateſt care muſt aye be had to maintaine firſt good will.</l>
               <l>Demaunde no queſtion ſharply, nor with curſt and cruell worde,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:63"/>
               <l> And eke thy ſelfe demaunded ſhalt an anſwere milde auorde.</l>
               <l>Diſpraiſe nor praiſe not any one for vice or vertue more</l>
               <l>Than Reaſon wills: a meane is beſt, kéepe ſtill the meane in ſtore.</l>
               <l>So like or elſe condemne, as he that heares thée may not ſay</l>
               <l>Good faith thy iudgement is but yll, thou wandreſt farre aſtray.</l>
               <l>Thou ſhalt not like the better with thy tongue in that thou doſt</l>
               <l>That ſpitefull ſting into the limmes of men in abſence thruſt.</l>
               <l>For ery one both markes the man and hateth him that railes</l>
               <l>Vpon a man behind his backe and with his tongue aſſailes.</l>
               <l>Do euer flée the flattring gueſt, nor flatter thou at all:</l>
               <l>For both offences grieuous are, nor this nor that is ſmall,</l>
               <l>When other ſpeake thée faire &amp; ſmooth haue euer this in thought</l>
               <l>That thoſe good fellowes gladly would for litle price be bought.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:63"/>
               <l> But when thou ſpekeſt an other faire, he will for ſuch a friende</l>
               <l>But litle giue that proues him but a gloſer in the ende.</l>
               <l>Accompt no more of great report that wicked wights beſtowe,</l>
               <l>Than if the cauſe were yll wheron this great renoume did growe:</l>
               <l>But thinke it praiſe that naughtie men deuiſe in thy defame,</l>
               <l>The chiefeſt praiſe is to offende the beaſt that liues with ſhame.</l>
               <l>'Tis harde to ſtoppe the open eares againſt the pleaſant call,</l>
               <l>And that was euer compted yet the greateſt praiſe of all.</l>
               <l>No other <hi>Syrenes</hi> ſure they were that wiſe <hi>Vlyſſes</hi> guylde,</l>
               <l>Than ſmooth &amp; pleſant ſpeaking tongs with falſhodes cunning fylde.</l>
               <l>They, they are Mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſters great inough to trap the wiſeſt man.</l>
               <l>Thou euer more muſt ſtande in dread of pleaſant language than</l>
               <l>Of rougher ſpéeche. For ſpitefull tong doth aye diſcouer vice,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:64"/>
               <l> Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gleining marcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts cloke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> crime and cog with craftie diſe.</l>
               <l>The pinching griefes that men diſeaſd do féele, they ſéeke to heale:</l>
               <l>But ſuch as neuer ake they ſcorne and tender neuer a deale</l>
               <l>But die therof or eare they thought ſuch miſchiefe would befall.</l>
               <l>The wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhewes to outward mark the Surgion will with ſmall</l>
               <l>And litle coſt procure to health: but that which hidden lies</l>
               <l>And rankles déepe, beguiles the man that is accompted wiſe.</l>
               <l>Do not deſire, but as thou art, at any time to ſéeme</l>
               <l>Among the people, couet not that they of thée do déeme</l>
               <l>More than in déede is reaſon why. Thy déedes and noble race</l>
               <l>Thy valiant prowes, thy grandſyres great bring not ſo much in place,</l>
               <l>Nor ſéeke thy linage to aduaunce thy ſelfe extolling ſo:</l>
               <l>For ſure it yll becomes a man his proper praiſe to ſhowe.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:64"/>
               <l> Nor is it ſéemely for a man an others friends allide</l>
               <l>And Gentrie to deface to much therby to quaile his pride.</l>
               <l>Let raging rancour neuer cauſe or malice moue thy braine</l>
               <l>To go about anothers fame or good report to ſtaine.</l>
               <l>Nor if thou couet great accompt of wiſdome, go about</l>
               <l>Nor be the ſounder of thyne owne good déedes, to ſette them out.</l>
               <l>For as no man of Reaſon will his follies blabbe abrode:</l>
               <l>So neither ſhould his vertues by himſelfe at all be ſhowde.</l>
               <l>The tale (they ſay) is nothing worth but yelds a beaſtly ſmell</l>
               <l>(Much more vntrue) that any in his proper praiſe doth tell.</l>
               <l>But couet rather ſo to deale as men may blaſe thy déedes,</l>
               <l>That thou a myrror mayſt become to Age that thée ſuccéedes.</l>
               <l>But he that blabs his beaſtly déedes and makes them knowne to all</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:65"/>
               <l> And tells his filthie trade of life, a frantike foole wée call.</l>
               <l>And whether it be true or falſe that he reporteth ſo,</l>
               <l>He well deſerues on Gallow trée to hang to féede the Crowe.</l>
               <l>But if thy fortune frame in ſort that thou vnknowne doſt liue,</l>
               <l>And doſt deſerue a greater fame than any man doth giue:</l>
               <l>Then ſomewhat in thy proper praiſe (with Modeſtie) thou mayſt</l>
               <l>Declare, but euer kéepe a meane in ery thyng thou ſayſt.</l>
               <l>Make men to vnderſtand if ought that famous is doth lye</l>
               <l>Within thy ſkill: but do procure them no offence therby.</l>
               <l>For no man vnder buſhell putts a candell bearing light,</l>
               <l>Or nearer than he ought vnto the thing applies his ſight.</l>
               <l>Vainglorie by no learning ſéeke that harbours in thy braine:</l>
               <l>He is vnwiſe that longs for that, All glorie is but vaine.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:65"/>
               <l> For whatſoeuer thing we doe accompliſhe worthie fame,</l>
               <l>It is not wée, but <hi>CHRIST,</hi> our King that doth atchieue the ſame.</l>
               <l>Wherfore to him is glorie due this boldly may we ſay:</l>
               <l>For holy Fathers of the Church ſo vſe in Church to pray.</l>
               <l>Then certainly the glorie that we men on men beſtow</l>
               <l>May vaine and light accompted bée, and fitly termed ſo.</l>
               <l>When ſo thou happen to controll or rate a man for yll,</l>
               <l>Séeme not to do it toucht with wrath, but for a méere good will.</l>
               <l>For oftentimes the bitter gueſt that chides in angry moode</l>
               <l>Doth profit nought, the pleaſant man is he that doth thée good.</l>
               <l>For he doth more a thouſande folde inſtruct and teach the way</l>
               <l>To vertue, than the chiding Carle that cruell words doth ſay.</l>
               <l>Who ſo vpon an Error doth vnwittingly amiſſe</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:66"/>
               <l> Deſerues a pardon at thy hands: but ſay vnto him thus,</l>
               <l>That if he doe in after time commit the like againe</l>
               <l>He ſhall be ſo releaſd no more but bide the ſharper paine.</l>
               <l>Then if thy wordes preuaile no whit but that within a ſpace</l>
               <l>He do the like offenſe againe, then put him in a place</l>
               <l>Aſſignde to tame ſuch retchloſſe Roges clappe fetters to his ſhanks,</l>
               <l>To ſtande aſſurde he ſhall no more go play ſuch beaſtly pranks</l>
               <l>Procéede not ouer far in chaufe, behoues thée too beware:</l>
               <l>Be not too ſharpe or curſt to thoſe to thée that ſtrangers are.</l>
               <l>If thou be wiſe doe deale therein as cunning Surgeons play,</l>
               <l>Who for to heale do ſwap the dead and rotten fleſh away:</l>
               <l>So thou pretending good to doe thy frendes with wiſdome rate,</l>
               <l>In ſéeking to reforme their faultes procure thy ſelfe no hate.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:66"/>
               <l> Wherfore controll but now and then be ſeldome in a heate:</l>
               <l>Vnleſſe there be committed wrong, and when none other feate</l>
               <l>Or way will ſerue the turne ſo well as chaufing will in déede.</l>
               <l>If any do the like againe to thée do take good héede,</l>
               <l>Accept his warning well in worth: to him that for good will</l>
               <l>Doth moniſhe thée, vſe no outrage no worde or language yll.</l>
               <l>For if vpon good reaſon he hath chidde thée, then no doubt</l>
               <l>He did thée good: if not vpon good cauſe, yet went about</l>
               <l>And minded he but well therin although thou déeme not ſo.</l>
               <l>At any time when ſo thou art defamed by thy foe,</l>
               <l>Or that he whet his rankling tuſkes againſt thy good report:</l>
               <l>Deale wiſely with ſuch bedlam beaſts in grane and ſober ſort.</l>
               <l>Oh, how much doth thy ſubtil foe vnweapned daunt thy pride,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:67"/>
               <l> When ſo he cauſer is that thou from good demeanor ſlide?</l>
               <l>Let from thy wiſe and ſober lips no word vnſéemely fall,</l>
               <l>Though he vnciuile beaſtly man in curriſh wiſe do braule.</l>
               <l>Beſides to voide the miſchiefe, and to ſtinte the ſtrife begon,</l>
               <l>Digreſſe thou from ſuch brauling flat and to the purpoſe roon.</l>
               <l>Deale in ſuch ſort as vnto thée may no man iuſtly ſay,</l>
               <l>What? (ſtop my frend) you ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gle now returne againe I pray.</l>
               <l>And when thou ſéeſt that irkeſom is thy proceſſe ouerlong</l>
               <l>Vnto thy felowes, ſhut thy pipes and ende thy lothſome ſong.</l>
               <l>Séeke not the loftie Marble houſe beſet with pictures braue,</l>
               <l>But couet aye the lodge where thou thy perfect health mayſt haue.</l>
               <l>And whether thou thy ſelfe doſt builde it vp, or buie the ſame,</l>
               <l>Prouide it ſuch a one as beſt vnto thy vſe may frame.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:67"/>
               <l> For ſithens Houſes builded are to onely vſe of man</l>
               <l>Let eche one get him ſuch a roome for profite as he can.</l>
               <l>Thou muſt not ſéeke for pleaſure of thy houſe ſo trimly dight,</l>
               <l>But rather in the beautie of thy ſecrete Soule delight.</l>
               <l>Whom if thou clenſe (no doubt) it wil ſtraunge odours yelde to thée,</l>
               <l>Wherin thou mayſt ſuch ſolace take as ſhall beſt liking bée.</l>
               <l>And where as in thy houſe thou ſtayſt but for a litle ſpace,</l>
               <l>Both day and night that other is to thée a dwellyng place.</l>
               <l>Then, let it bée thy onely care to decke it paſſing fine</l>
               <l>With precious perfumes ſwete to ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe do make it freſhly ſhine:</l>
               <l>In ſort the owner may not by his houſe ſo famous bée,</l>
               <l>As may thy houſe and dwelling place accompted of by thée.</l>
               <l>It is vnſéemely that a man ſhould horow all his praiſe</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:68"/>
               <l> From lodge wherin but for a time and ſtraungerlike he ſtayes.</l>
               <l>But let the lodging ſomewhat ayde the maiſters good report,</l>
               <l>And helpe as much as lies in it to ſet to ſhewe his porte.</l>
               <l>But take good héede the ſaying olde be not applyde to thée,</l>
               <l>O Lorde, how far this Owner, and this houſe doe diſagrée?</l>
               <l>For oftentimes my ſelfe haue heard men ſay, and that of late:</l>
               <l>O worthie auncient houſe, how muche diminiſht is thy ſtate?</l>
               <l>Again in Countrey build thy Graunge no greater than it ſhould,</l>
               <l>But kéepe the cuſtome aye therin, a Coate to baniſhe colde.</l>
               <l>Thy hand, thy ieſture, lips and lookes doe gouerne in ſuch wiſe</l>
               <l>As men may well diſcerne the thing within thy breaſt that lies.</l>
               <l>And all ſuch ieſtures as thou déemſte in others fonde to bée,</l>
               <l>Accompt it will not very well vnto thy kinde agrée.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:68"/>
               <l> But if thou doubt at all therof, go ſéeke thy friends aduice</l>
               <l>That will inſtruct in ery poynt what moſt agrées with vice.</l>
               <l>For ſo doe cunning Painters deale and Poets of the beſt:</l>
               <l>They aſke how other men do like their Pictures lately dreſt.</l>
               <l>Beſides to gayne a heape of wealth and to increaſe thy ſtore,</l>
               <l>Thou ſhalt not follow filthy artes at any time the more</l>
               <l>But euer ſhoon the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſtly gayne whence hate and enuie ſprings.</l>
               <l>Wherfore thou ſhalt not kéepe a Port to looke and ſearch for things</l>
               <l>That paſſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to forain Realms: nor Fulkers trade enſue</l>
               <l>By taking money for the loane as though it were thy due.</l>
               <l>Thou ſhalt not follow Butchers craft in ſhambles leading life,</l>
               <l>For gain to knocke the bullocks head, and cut his throate with knife.</l>
               <l>Thou ſhalt not play the Hukſter, for theſe Artes that I haue ſayd</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:69"/>
               <l> Are vile, vncleanly, baſe of kinde, and nothing to be wayd.</l>
               <l>And all thoſe other trades of life are to be compted vaine</l>
               <l>That all in worke conſiſte, and nought in beating of the braine:</l>
               <l>And that for money are to bye, which witte can neuer bee:</l>
               <l>Wherfore doe force no one of them if thou be rulde by mée.</l>
               <l>There reſtes no wit in ought that is ſet out to open ſale,</l>
               <l>No good increaſe of knowledge comes by Bellyfare and Ale.</l>
               <l>The Dicing Dick, and Daun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ng boy purſue no honeſt trade:</l>
               <l>The Pedlar eke that beares his packe himſelfe for lacke of Iade</l>
               <l>Is nothing to be compted, or the Mercer that doth buye</l>
               <l>And ſells his traſhe within a while doth vſe full oft to lie,</l>
               <l>And like a periurde patch doth prate and all to get a gaine:</l>
               <l>And ſure than him that is forſworne can nothing be more vaine.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:69"/>
               <l> For why he crafts with man, and doth yea God himſelfe deſpiſe.</l>
               <l>But if ſo be that one become a Merchant man, and plies</l>
               <l>His matters ſo as wealthie he is woxen by the ſame,</l>
               <l>And hath his ſtorehouſe full of wares, he doth deſerue no ſhame,</l>
               <l>Nor worthie is in my conceite a foule rebuke to beare,</l>
               <l>But rather praiſe for doing ſo if he at laſt forbeare</l>
               <l>His merchants trade and fall to plough and waxe a Countreyman:</l>
               <l>For better than the tillage of the ſoyle there lightly can</l>
               <l>Be nothing or of greater ſame, that takes ſo litle ſéede</l>
               <l>And yeldes againe ſuch great increaſe to pleaſure vs at néede.</l>
               <l>This trade of yore the Noble men that Conquerours became</l>
               <l>Of taking of the plough in hande and culter did not ſhame,</l>
               <l>They neuer bluſht to breake the ſoyle: the <hi>Romaine</hi> Court did call</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:70"/>
               <l> The Fathers that appointed were to rule and gouerne all,</l>
               <l>And fet them from the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey Coat: and he that is as now</l>
               <l>The Conſull, bearyng all the ſway of late did driue the Plowe.</l>
               <l>Of all the other trades I know Phyſitions beare the bell,</l>
               <l>And he is worthie praiſe that builds a houſe for men to dwell.</l>
               <l>To buie an office be not thou too quicke or ſharply ſet:</l>
               <l>But when thou haſt it frankly giuen or offred thée, do get</l>
               <l>And take it yelding worthie thanks. Beléeue not ery lie</l>
               <l>That rumor ſpreds, or brute doth cauſe in open ayre to flie:</l>
               <l>For often vile and wicked heads no trouth at all deuiſe.</l>
               <l>And many times the naughtieſt men in ſmooth and ſimple guiſe</l>
               <l>Do blaze vntrouthes to wrong y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> good: as much as lies in thée</l>
               <l>Confounde and do reſiſt their trade, and what they ſay do flée.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:70"/>
               <l> And what they doe, in any eaſe do barre it by and maine.</l>
               <l>Indeuor in thy happie ſtate to be in pleaſant vaine:</l>
               <l>For then thy powre doth ſerue thée beſt then mayſt thou pleaſant bée,</l>
               <l>Yea, though thy welth be ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>what ſhort goe hunt abroade for glée,</l>
               <l>Leaſt euery man accompt of thée as of a miſer wight.</l>
               <l>Beware when thou lamentſt thy haps thou neuer do recite</l>
               <l>Commodities of other men: leſt they doe déeme that thou</l>
               <l>Doſt ſpit and ſwel at their good lucke whome Fortune doth allow.</l>
               <l>Be earneſt euermore to learne, but ſée thou force nowhit</l>
               <l>What one he is that doth inſtruct ſo he do teach thée right</l>
               <l>And hauing ſkill impart the ſame to ſuch as do deſire</l>
               <l>With gréedy minds to light their torch or candle at thy fire.</l>
               <l>Remembre that thy ſelfe didſt learne of other men before.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21003:71"/>
               <l> My <hi>Muſe Thaleya</hi> holde thy hande, procéede (I ſay) no more,</l>
               <l>But ende thy vndertaken worke: if ought be left vnfolde</l>
               <l>When better time hereafter ſerues thou ſhalt at full vnfolde.</l>
               <l>Do pardon (Reader) if that I my race too farre haue roon,</l>
               <l>For ſure my <hi>Muſe</hi> did meane thée well when I this Booke begoon.</l>
               <l>A Path to Pleaſure thée alone, a Meane to finde the way</l>
               <l>To perfect Vertue, where ſhe ſitts and kéepes this earth in ſtay.</l>
            </div>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
            <closer>
               <signed>G. T.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:21003:71"/>
            <head>The Tranſlater to the Booke.</head>
            <l>FArewell thou litle booke an other mans and mine,</l>
            <l>The Gods allowe thée bleſſed hap, report without repine.</l>
            <l>Well mayſt thou liked be. and ſo thou ſhalt I truſt,</l>
            <l>Of ſuch as Vertue do imbrace: as for the reſt thou muſt</l>
            <l>Appoint vpon as foes. I meane the ſinfull ſect,</l>
            <l>That neither thée for Vertues ſake, nor Vertue will reſpect.</l>
            <l>Was neuer man that wrote of Vertue yet a whit</l>
            <l>But Enuie would with malice ſéeke his trauaile to requite.</l>
            <l>But force thou not at all, be bolde and neuer bluſhe:</l>
            <l>For Glorie euer gaines the byrde where Enuie beates the buſhe.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:21003:72"/>
            <l> Sith thou of Vertue doſt and nothing elſe intreate,</l>
            <l>I know thy foes are friends to Vice, with wrath and yre repleate.</l>
            <l>With them thou haſt to deale: thou knoweſt the wonted ſawe.</l>
            <l>The Iade will kicke at him that rubbs his backe if it be rawe.</l>
            <l>Then ſith thou prickſt with pen the galled backe, be ſure</l>
            <l>Thou ſhalt deſpite, in ſteade of loue of wicked wights procure.</l>
            <l>For trouth doth purchaſe hate, and reapes that fruite for gaine</l>
            <l>A bad reward for good deſert. But wotſt thou what againe?</l>
            <l>The better ſort of men will like thy purpoſe well,</l>
            <l>And ring thy praiſe by good report as loude as Larum bell.</l>
            <l>If be that pende thée firſt, and brought thée forth to light</l>
            <l>Could finde in heart to hazarde thée to hands of fowle deſpite:</l>
            <l>Why ſhould I more accompt to kéepe thée vnder wing</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:21003:72"/>
            <l> That onely phraſe for phraſe tranſlate and verſe to Metre bring?</l>
            <l>Thou art no new deuiſe, the wéede wherin thou were</l>
            <l>Is ſomewhat altred, but I truſt <hi>Mancinus</hi> néede not feare</l>
            <l>Or ſtande in doubt of thée, he ſhall not looſe his right:</l>
            <l>I would not go about to wrong a <hi>Romane</hi> if I might.</l>
            <l>But for deſire to make <hi>Mancinus</hi> better knowne,</l>
            <l>I toylde anewe the ſoyle that he with painefull plough had ſowne.</l>
            <l>I truſt he ſhall not loath our mother tong at all:</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Mancinus</hi> is <hi>Mancinus</hi> ſtill I truſt and euer ſhall.</l>
            <l>And thus to ende my tale I wiſhe (thée litle Booke)</l>
            <l>To doe no worſe than him that doth vpon thy Vertues looke.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>IMPRINTED AT LONDON in Knight Rider ſtreate, by Henry Bynneman, for L. Maylerd.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
